<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>Nex</title>
        <description>The personal website of Claudio Guarnieri, alias Nex.
</description>
        <link>https://nex.sx</link>
        <atom:link href="https://nex.sx/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
        
        <item>
            <title>More on Mobile Security and Device Integrity</title>
            <description>&lt;p&gt;In my previous newsletter&lt;sup id=&quot;a1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#f1&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; I comment on the recent news regarding the WhatsApp exploits discovered used by NSO Group and I marginally touch on the difficulties we encounter in confirming infections of mobile devices, particularly because of the tight security mitigations implemented by manufacturers such as Google and Apple.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some additional debate and commentary appeared on social media, particularly after an article published by Motherboard&lt;sup id=&quot;a1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#f1&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; expanding on this particular issue, and quoting various security researchers as well as my newsletter. Because it is an interesting and contentious topic, I figured I could expand on my point. Forgive the higher frequency of my writing, but it’s dicated by timeliness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my previous newsletter, I wrote:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“… these security controls have made mobile devices extremely difficult to inspect, especially remotely, and particularly for those of us working in human rights organizations lacking access to adequate forensics technology.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And continued:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Quite frankly, we are on the losing side of a disheartening asymmetry of capabilities that favors attackers over us, defenders.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What do I mean by that?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What perhaps many don’t realize is how resourceless we are, as technologists, when asked to respond to a suspected attack or to inspect a mobile device of an individual at risk who might have been targeted. For example, if a human rights defender suspects they are being surveilled and they bring their iPhone for inspection, all we can mostly do is search for suspicious messages and perhaps monitor the outgoing network traffic for the amount of time available to us (generally not a lot) hoping to get lucky enough to spot some suspicious traces at the right time. Obviously, when there is a significant distance or travel restrictions, our ability to intervene reduces drastically.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Under some circumstances there are exceptions and we might be able to do more. More commonly, however, technical, logistical and time constraints do not allow for a meaningful analysis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although the tight security controls baked into modern mobile devices are a net positive and significantly raise the costs for attackers, when the threat model of an individual at risk includes a nation state or even a law enforcement agency among their adversaries, these limitations play into the losing asymmetry of capabilities I mentioned in my previous newsletter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why? Because various companies out there are resourceful enough to acquire the necessary talent and the necessary technology (sometimes illegally&lt;sup id=&quot;a3&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#f3&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;) and research and develop bypasses to smartphones’ security mitigations. Companies such as NSO Group, or even Cellebrite&lt;sup id=&quot;a4&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#f4&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and GrayShift&lt;sup id=&quot;a5&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#f5&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, provide expensive products and services to States, which can essentially exercise an hegemonic power over the subversion of modern mobile devices for offensive purposes. In other words, there are tools available to law enforcement and intelligence agencies to break into an iPhone unknowingly to its owner, while there is very little available to us to inspect a smartphone even when the owner is willing to unlock it in front of us. I am sure it is superflous to explain why exclusively relying on law enforcement agencies or manufacturers is often not scalable or simply not possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regardless of the legitimacy or illegitimacy of this imbalance, I believe it is an objective reality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The resulting question then is: what can be done to enable people (especially individuals at risk and their support networks) to obtain more agency over their own mobile devices? Modern smartphones are very closed system, and perhaps for the owners’ own good. Balancing a product’s default security hardening with more access for its owner is not trivial. Some on social media rightfully argued&lt;sup id=&quot;a6&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#f6&quot;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; that opening up access for third-party security vendors to more closely inspect mobile devices will most likely result in that same access abused by malicious actors for offensive purposes. I agree. However, I also believe that more needs to be done (or at least explored) to provide at least some ability for consumers to independently verify the integrity of their devices. Even only within boundaries and with tools designed by the manufacturers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other than the obvious technical value of being able to determine whether a device is being tampered with (at any time, and under the owner’s own security and personal safety requirements) and adapt one’s secure communications strategy, enabling individuals at risk to learn whether their smartphones are being used to surveil them can also be an extremely important canary in the coalmine to alert them, and to contextualize their current exposure to personal risk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I’m left to wonder is whether some of these changes would be technically and economically justifiable for manufacturers, in contrast to the needs of a larger consumer base and the interests of shareholders. I don’t know. I suppose that is the unfortunate result of the largely monolithic technological ecosystem in which we live.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;f1&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;1: &lt;a href=&quot;https://nex.sx/blog/2019/05/14/on-whatsapp-0day-legal-action-nso.html&quot;&gt;On the WhatsApp 0day and legal action against NSO Group - Nex&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span id=&quot;f2&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;2: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.vice.com/en_us/article/pajkkz/its-almost-impossible-to-tell-if-iphone-has-been-hacked&quot;&gt;It’s Almost Impossible to Tell if Your iPhone Has Been Hacked - VICE&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span id=&quot;f3&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;3: &lt;a href=&quot;https://motherboard.vice.com/en_us/article/gyakgw/the-prototype-dev-fused-iphones-that-hackers-use-to-research-apple-zero-days&quot;&gt;The Prototype iPhones That Hackers Use to Research Apple’s Most Sensitive Code - VICE&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span id=&quot;f4&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;4: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.washingtonpost.com/world/asia_pacific/security-tech-companies-once-flocked-to-myanmar-one-firms-tools-were-used-against-two-journalists-/2019/05/04/d4e9f7f0-5b5d-11e9-b8e3-b03311fbbbfe_story.html&quot;&gt;Security-tech companies once flocked to Myanmar. One firm’s tools were used against two journalists&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span id=&quot;f5&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;5: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.forbes.com/sites/thomasbrewster/2018/03/05/apple-iphone-x-graykey-hack/&quot;&gt;Mysterious $15,000 ‘GrayKey’ Promises To Unlock iPhone X For The Feds&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span id=&quot;f6&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;6: &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/DidymaWorks/status/1128314170057748491&quot;&gt;Twitter&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
            <pubDate>Wed, 15 May 2019 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
            <link>https://nex.sx//blog/2019/05/15/more-on-mobile-security-and-device-integrity.html</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://nex.sx//blog/2019/05/15/more-on-mobile-security-and-device-integrity.html</guid>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>On the WhatsApp 0day and legal action against NSO Group</title>
            <description>&lt;p&gt;The Israeli spyware firm NSO Group is in the news again today. Facebook discovered a critical vulnerability in the WhatsApp messenger apparently being leveraged in attacks set to install NSO Group’s Pegasus spyware on the targets’ phones&lt;sup id=&quot;a1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#f1&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Facebook (who owns WhatsApp) announced today the discovery, released an emergency update for WhatsApp and disclosed some details&lt;sup id=&quot;a2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#f2&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. The vulnerability seems to lie in WhatsApp’s VoIP implementation, and would allow the attackers to remotely infect a mobile device just by instantiating some video calls through the app. Because no interaction on the victim’s part is needed, this exploit is being referred to on the press as “0-click” (zero-click).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are some considerations I would like to share in reaction to this story.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Firstly, while it is a significant story and the exploit discovered by Facebook and likely developed by NSO Group is potent and worrying, we should not consider this an isolated or unprecedented case. Unfortunately, so called “0-click” exploits are more common than it appears on the press, and blaming WhatsApp for this security flaw is shortsighted, as we can surely expect competitor apps to be equally targeted and most likely already exploited. As a matter of fact, only few months ago Reuters reported that the UAE exploited similar vulnerabilities in iMessage as part of “Project Raven”&lt;sup id=&quot;a3&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#f3&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Essentially, because an exploit in WhatsApp was now discovered, it does not mean other apps are inherently more secure. If anything, it speaks to the difficulty to uncover these attacks even by large and resourceful security teams such as that of Facebook, let alone by smaller organisations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The amount of documented cases of targeting of journalists and human rights defenders using NSO Group’s products and services is evergrowing. And although we expect more to come to light in the future, all that we know so far is most likely a small fraction of the whole. Attacking and infecting mobile devices is a difficult, but not impossible, task because of the many security mitigations and lockdowns baked into mobile platforms, such as Android and even more so iOS. However, these security controls have made mobile devices extremely difficult to inspect, especially remotely, and particularly for those of us working in human rights organizations lacking access to adequate forensics technology. Because of this, we are rarely able to confirm infections of those who we even already suspect being targeted. Last August, for example, we discovered one of our Amnesty staff members was targeted with Pegasus&lt;sup id=&quot;a4&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#f4&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; but whether others were too is not possible for us to confirm. Quite frankly, we are on the losing side of a disheartening asymmetry of capabilities that favors attackers over us, defenders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The darker reality is that NSO Group is just one of many, many more surveillance firms operating in the same space. NSO is getting caught in public more regularly probably because of their larger market share, but also because there is existing documentation for security researchers out there, such as those at Facebook who discovered this WhatsApp exploit, who can at least marginally follow NSO Group’s breadcrumbs. For this we can thank Ahmed Mansoor, who first came forward with messages that led to the discovery of Pegasus, and who is now enduring a hunger strike in the jail where he’s serving an unjust 10 years sentence&lt;sup id=&quot;a5&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#f5&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Additionally, I believe the technical limitations I described earlier also contribute to the reason why not more similar exploits and spyware are discovered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, human rights defenders are losing the most. The widespread use of exploits and spyware, the seemingly unaccountable business of the firms producing them, and a worrying lack of forensics and intrusion detection technologies available to members of civil society, all contribute to a sense of dooming inevitability. That is why we, at Amnesty International, are taking action. On Monday, we have filed a legal complaint to the Israeli Minister of Defense requesting the withdrawal of the export license for NSO Group&lt;sup id=&quot;a6&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#f6&quot;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Amnesty along with many other organisations have also demanded transparency and accountability to Novalpina Capital and the other financial institutions invested in the company&lt;sup id=&quot;a7&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#f7&quot;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. These legal battles are new tactics that will be put to test over the next years in courts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the meantime, our Digital Security Lab at Amnesty International and all our technologists around the world have been working hard to build capacity to properly support individuals at risk. While publications are important for advocacy and awareness, I believe they are not enough alone. We need to seriously invest in providing human rights defenders with the practical means and the tools to prevent and respond to cyber attacks effectively. We are working towards this goal, and I am looking forward to share more about this in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As always, if you have information to share that can help us discover and stop campaigns of illegitimate hacking of members of civil society, don’t hesitate to get in contact with me&lt;sup id=&quot;a8&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#f8&quot;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;f1&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;1: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2019/05/13/technology/nso-group-whatsapp-spying.html&quot;&gt;Israeli Firm Tied to Tool That Uses WhatsApp Flaw to Spy on Activists - The New York Times&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span id=&quot;f2&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;2: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facebook.com/security/advisories/cve-2019-3568&quot;&gt;Facebook&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span id=&quot;f3&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;3: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reuters.com/investigates/special-report/usa-spying-raven/&quot;&gt;Exclusive: Ex-NSA cyberspies reveal how they helped hack foes of UAE&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span id=&quot;f4&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;4: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amnesty.org/en/latest/research/2018/08/amnesty-international-among-targets-of-nso-powered-campaign/&quot;&gt;Amnesty International Among Targets of NSO-powered Campaign | Amnesty International&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span id=&quot;f5&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;5: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amnesty.org/en/latest/news/2019/04/uae-ahmed-mansoor-enters-fourth-week-of-hunger-strike-to-protest-unfair-10-year-sentence/&quot;&gt;UAE: Ahmed Mansoor enters fourth week of hunger strike to protest unfair 10-year sentence | Amnesty International&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span id=&quot;f6&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;6: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amnesty.org/en/latest/news/2019/05/israel-amnesty-legal-action-stop-nso-group-web-of-surveillance/&quot;&gt;Israel: Amnesty International engages in legal action to stop NSO Group’s web of surveillance | Amnesty International&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span id=&quot;f7&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;7: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amnesty.org/en/latest/research/2019/02/open-letter-to-novalpina-capital-nso-group-and-francisco-partners/&quot;&gt;Open letter to Novalpina Capital, CC: NSO Group, Francisco Partners &lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span id=&quot;f8&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;8: &lt;a href=&quot;https://nex.sx/contacts/&quot;&gt;Contacts - Nex&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
            <pubDate>Tue, 14 May 2019 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
            <link>https://nex.sx//blog/2019/05/14/on-whatsapp-0day-legal-action-nso.html</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://nex.sx//blog/2019/05/14/on-whatsapp-0day-legal-action-nso.html</guid>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Exodus: How the Discovery of a Malware Revealed a Spy Scandal in Italy</title>
            <description>&lt;p&gt;On Friday 29th Security Without Borders in collaboration with Motherboard published a new investigation into a previously unknown surveillance vendor from Italy called eSurv.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://securitywithoutborders.org/blog/2019/03/29/exodus.html&quot;&gt;https://securitywithoutborders.org/blog/2019/03/29/exodus.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This company, which purported to only be a surveillance cameras manufacturer, in reality has been producing intrusion software (spyware) since at least 2016. We dubbed this spyware “Exodus” after a domain name used as Command &amp;amp; Control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://motherboard.vice.com/en_us/article/43z93g/hackers-hid-android-malware-in-google-play-store-exodus-esurv&quot;&gt;https://motherboard.vice.com/en_us/article/43z93g/hackers-hid-android-malware-in-google-play-store-exodus-esurv&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As originally noted by Motherboard through publicly available documents, and as now confirmed by public prosecutor’s offices, this software was in use by law enforcement all over Italy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What made this software particularly worrying for us was, firstly, that it was widely distributed through the Google Play Store and publicly accessible for anybody to install. As a matter of fact, hundreds of installations were registered across 25 different copies of the spyware. Secondly, the spyware is able to collect much more information than what is normally mandated by law in Italy. Thirdly, the spyware would establish  unencrypted reverse shells to the Command &amp;amp; Control, that could be prone to man-in-the-middle attacks. Lastly, and even more worryingly in my mind, it would enable terminal access to the device by simply connecting to various fixed TCP port numbers, effectively leaving the phone exposed to further compromise or data tampering by anybody who would share the same network (such as a public Wi-Fi, or potentially even the same cellular network).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This story gained significant attention on Italian press and received coverage on all major newspapers, online and print, as well as on prime time television news on Saturday. While the initial press coverage wasn’t particularly accurate, it opened up to some interesting and unexpected developments that are still unfolding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The prosecutor of Napoli informed the press that an investigation was active on the company and that few days prior to our publication a judge issued a seizure warrant for eSurv and its assets, as well as another company, STM s.r.l.&lt;sup id=&quot;a1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#f1&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Italian press reports that STM s.r.l. had numerous contracts with public prosecutor’s offices across Italy to setup and maintain the Exodus system they purchased from eSurv. The prosecutor’s office of Benevento recently realized, during yet another apparent malfunction, that the Exodus spyware in their use wasn’t exfiltrating and storing data on the local server in the premises of the office (as mandated by Italian law), but on Amazon cloud instances instead. As a matter of fact, the press reports, the server provided to the public prosecutor’s office wasn’t even equipped with an Operating System, and contained no data at all. Essentially it was an empty box. Additionally, it appears that interception data from invesigations by several other public prosecutor’s offices was stored on this same Amazon instance, and that the companies maintained privileged access.&lt;sup id=&quot;a2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#f2&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is wild.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Exodus servers are being analyzed and people are being investigated. It is unclear currently what was the purpose and who was the operator of the malicious apps we discovered on the Play Store and how many of the hundreds of victims were intended and how many were accidental.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More recent reports are now suggesting that the story might go deeper and darker than originally anticipated. The press is currently suggesting that illegal spying might have been operated on behalf of unknown entities&lt;sup id=&quot;a3&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#f3&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and that this investigation is crossing with separate investigations dealing with corruption in Calabria&lt;sup id=&quot;a4&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#f4&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By all accounts, it seems that this story is still unfolding. More information will likely follow as more details from the investigations will come to light.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hopefully, this case will reinvigorate a much needed debate on the nature of lawful interception intrusion software and the Wild West that is the industry behind it. In these years we have mostly debated on how to properly export these technologies out of Europe, but if anything, this case should highlight the very serious legal, technical, and constitutional issues raised by its current use here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;f1&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;1: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ilfattoquotidiano.it/2019/04/01/exodus-4-indagati-a-napoli-intercettati-illegalmente-centinaia-di-italiani-dati-giudiziari-salvati-su-un-cloud-amazon/5078359/&quot;&gt;Exodus, 4 indagati a Napoli. Intercettati illegalmente centinaia di italiani: “Dati giudiziari salvati su un cloud Amazon” - Il Fatto Quotidiano&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span id=&quot;f2&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;2: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ilfattoquotidiano.it/2019/04/02/benevento-software-spia-farlocchi-e-server-giudiziari-vuoti-sui-cloud-amazon-anche-le-intercettazioni-di-altre-procure/5079009/&quot;&gt;Benevento, software spia farlocchi e server giudiziari vuoti: sui cloud Amazon anche le intercettazioni di altre procure - Il Fatto Quotidiano&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span id=&quot;f3&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;3: &lt;a href=&quot;https://roma.corriere.it/notizie/cronaca/19_aprile_01/sospetto-dossieraggi-ricatti-il-software-spia-telefonini-c2347232-54b6-11e9-a9e2-a0d1446d1611.shtml&quot;&gt;Il sospetto di dossieraggi e ricatti con il software spia nei telefonini - Corriere.it&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span id=&quot;f4&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;4: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.corrieredellacalabria.it/regione/cosenza/item/181508-magistrati-e-investigatori-gli-amici-calabresi-del-poliziotto-della-spy-story/&quot;&gt;Magistrati e investigatori, gli amici calabresi del poliziotto della “spy story” - Corriere della Calabria&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
            <pubDate>Thu, 04 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
            <link>https://nex.sx//blog/2019/04/04/exodus-spy-scandal-italy.html</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://nex.sx//blog/2019/04/04/exodus-spy-scandal-italy.html</guid>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Phishing Attacks Using Third-Party Applications Against Egyptian Civil Society Organizations</title>
            <description>&lt;p&gt;I am aware that most of my recent newsletters dealt with the issue of account security and phishing, but I have one more story on this to share with you. I suppose this is indicative of the sad nature of the digital (in)security we face today. I promise, in the newsletters to come I will cover other topics as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, we published a short blog post warning of an ongoing campaign of phishing attacks targeting human rights defenders and NGOs from Egypt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amnesty.org/en/latest/research/2019/03/phishing-attacks-using-third-party-applications-against-egyptian-civil-society-organizations/&quot;&gt;https://www.amnesty.org/en/latest/research/2019/03/phishing-attacks-using-third-party-applications-against-egyptian-civil-society-organizations/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To quote directly from the report:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Since January 2019 several human rights defenders and civil society organizations from Egypt started forwarding dozens of suspicious emails to Amnesty International. Through the course of our investigation we discovered that these emails were attempts to access the email accounts of their targets through a particularly insidious form of phishing known as OAuth Phishing (which we explain in detail below). We estimate the total number of targeted individuals to be in the order of several hundreds.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“These coincided with a number of important events that took place in the country. In the run-up to the eighth anniversary of Egypt’s 25 January uprising, which ended with the removal of former president Hosni Mubarak, after 30 years in power, we recorded 11 phishing attacks against NGOs and media collectives. We saw another burst of attacks during French President Emmanuel Macron’s visit to Cairo to meet with President Abdelfatah al-Sisi on 28 and 29 January. The attacks peaked on 29 January, the day that President Macron met with human rights defenders from four prominent Egyptian NGOs. Later, in the first week of February, several media organizations were targeted as part of this campaign of digital attacks; they were reporting on the process of amending the Egyptian Constitution that the parliament had just officially started.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OAuth Phishing is an insidious phishing technique that is not very common, and consequently not as widely known to individuals at risk as the more traditional forms of phishing. Additionally, security education material rarely includes mentions of OAuth Phishing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Essentially, OAuth Phishing relies on a feature that is commonly available with many email providers (such as Google, Yahoo, Hotmail and Outlook) that allows people to grant third-party applications access to their accounts. Legitimate third-party applications could be designed to, for example, extract invitations or flight and hotel bookings from the email inbox and add them to an external calendar application.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Attackers can abuse this feature and create malicious third-party applications that are masqueraded as legitimate while in reality their purpose is to steal the emails from the victim.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the blog post we provide additional details and visuals explaining how this attack works and how to mitigate against it. Unfortunately, because this form of phishing does not rely on creating and distributing a fake login prompt for a legitimate service, but abuses the service directly, the only prevention is to be alert and suspicious of third-party applications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we highlight in the blog post, the targets of this latest campaign in Egypt significantly overlap with the targets of a similar phishing campaign discovered two years ago. At the time, the attackers set up the typical Google login clones and lured targets into giving away their credentials. Since then, human rights defenders and NGOs have equipped themselves with two-factor authentication solutions that mitigated that form of phishing. Now, the attackers have clearly adapted and the use of OAuth Phishing seems like a direct response to the better security practices that have been adopted by their targets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Attackers are agile in their tactics, we need to be as agile in our defenses.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
            <pubDate>Fri, 08 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
            <link>https://nex.sx//blog/2019/03/08/phishing-attacks-against-egyptian-civil-society.html</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://nex.sx//blog/2019/03/08/phishing-attacks-against-egyptian-civil-society.html</guid>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>The Death of The Exploit</title>
            <description>&lt;p&gt;Matt Miller, from Microsoft Security Response Center, delivered a very interesting presentation at the Bluehat conference few days ago titled “Trends, challenges, and strategic shifts in the software vulnerability mitigation landscape”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this presentation Matt, who is otherwise known as “skape” and is recognized for his many years of work on exploit research and his contributions to the Metasploit project, provided a very interesting overview of the progress made over the last decade on tackling software vulnerabilities. I very much recommending reading the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/Microsoft/MSRC-Security-Research/blob/master/presentations/2019_02_BlueHatIL/2019_&quot;&gt;slides&lt;/a&gt; and I hope a video recording will be made available soon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are several takeaways from this presentation, and those I found most relevant are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1) While the amount of known software vulnerabilities reported every year follows an increasing trajectory, the percentage of those that are actually exploited in the wild is decreasing.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This highlights an interesting discrepancy which is hard to recognize for those who do not have access to telemetry such as Microsoft’s: while software vulnerabilities appear to be piling up like never before, attackers are leveraging fewer. This is an interesting trend and while I can imagine a variety of factors that might be influencing this shift, I would be interested in hearing more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2) Increasingly more often, software vulnerabilities are found to be exploited for the first time as 0days, rather than after a patch is released.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Publicly available exploits are becoming less effective, possibly because of more dedicated update mechanisms employed by recent versions of Windows, and less reliable, thanks to the various mitigation techniques introduced in the last years. Leveraging a patched vulnerability now is most likely to be unsuccessful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, we need to wary of generalizations. Especially in countries with economic difficulties and even more so in countries subjected to embargoes, the availability of most recent hardware and software might be limited, particularly at the cost of individuals at risk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3) Exploit mitigations have had a significant impact, and we might see a day not too far away where software vulnerabilities are not as much of a concern anymore.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Essentially, things are getting better. With the exception of WannaCry, mass-spreading threats have nearly disappeared and so has the pandemic exploitation of browsers and plugins and of productivity suites.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been making similar observations in my monitoring of state-sponsored campaigns. While some years ago the largest majority of attacks were almost expected to make use of an Adobe Reader or Office exploit (ah, the good old CVE-2012-0158 days!) now any exploit at all is a rare sight for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the last couple of years I have been doing the exercise of looking back at all disclosed campaigns of targeted attacks against civil society from the previous year and try to derive some patterns and trends. With the exception of some high profile cases, such as those of NSO Group, the cases in which any exploit at all (0day or not) was used are near zero.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead, way more predominant is the abuse of certain Windows and Office features that are primarily intended for enterprises but are also a perfect attack surface for end users (such as Macros, OLE, DDE, PowerShell, etc.) and reflect a &lt;a href=&quot;https://nex.sx/blog/2017/01/11/on-banality-of-attacks.html&quot;&gt;lack of care for the needs of individuals at risk&lt;/a&gt;. In addition, more recently credentials phishing seems to be making a &lt;a href=&quot;https://nex.sx/blog/2018/12/20/phishing-2fa-and-false-myths.html&quot;&gt;strong return&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a matter of fact, I believe we are currently witnessing a bigger investment in improving credential phishing frameworks and tactics than in developing spyware. The spyware we observe is generally rudimentary and, while I have no solid data to back this up, I believe spyware’s return of investment is getting comparatively lower than that of phishing. The infection rate is quite likely significantly decreasing and at no discount of operational costs. Phishing instead largely remains an unsolved problem and it is quantitatively the most common threat we observe these days. Although I very wildly estimate a success rate generally below 10%, it’s an attack that is cheap to develop and operate and is reusable almost indefinitely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Getting back to software vulnerabilities and exploits, Matt writes in his presentation that Microsoft’s strategy against them is turning from “increasing cost &amp;amp; difficulty” to “getting to done”. It’s comforting to think we might eventually be “done” with exploits, but if we learned anything out of decades of cybersecurity is that the death of the exploit might just be the birth of something new.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
            <pubDate>Wed, 13 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
            <link>https://nex.sx//blog/2019/02/13/the-death-of-the-exploit.html</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://nex.sx//blog/2019/02/13/the-death-of-the-exploit.html</guid>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>The Losing Battle of Phishing Education</title>
            <description>&lt;p&gt;Today Google Jigsaw launched a new resource self-descriptively called Phishing Quiz. I generally applaud these efforts and I myself often recur to quizzes in my occasional trainings. This one is well designed and straightforward to use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://phishingquiz.withgoogle.com/&quot;&gt;https://phishingquiz.withgoogle.com/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The declared purpose of these quizzes is to enable potential at-risk individuals to train their eyes in spotting suspicious elements in email messages and web pages. For me, the purpose is rather to highlight the difficulty in recognizing well-crafted phishing attacks, and the numerous design inconsistencies across online service providers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Google’s quiz perfectly highlights many of these inconsistencies, and I invite you to try it for yourself. I did the same and at the end of it I tried to anticipate how an individual approaching this subject for the first time might leave confused.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Training individuals to detect phishing attacks through visual references is hard, because those don’t follow a logic shared across platforms and because they change occasionally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;[SPOILER ALERT: I am going to reference certain results from the Google Phishing Quiz, so do not read further if you don’t want any anticipations.]&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this quiz the primary two key visual elements the exercises are based upon are the email sender’s address and the links contained in the body of the message. Ideally, through this, individuals should identify patterns and construct a mental model to apply to any similar real-case scenario. However, we immediately see inconsistencies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In one exercise we are suggested that an email is in fact legitimate because, along with the validity of a contained link, the sender’s email address contain the domain @dropboxmail.com, which is an actual domain in use by Dropbox instead of the more intuitive @dropbox.com. At the same time, however, a different exercise alerts us that an email sender with @google.support is malicious because the domain is not in use by Google.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps an agreement among service providers to all adopt a similar scheme would be beneficial. For example, instead of using various domain names, all should stick to their primary domain for email communications, e.g. &lt;em&gt;noreply@dropbox.com&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;noreply@google.com&lt;/em&gt; instead of &lt;em&gt;dropboxmail.com&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;googlemail.com&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When it comes to links contained in the body of email messages we could expect similar confusion. Forged domains intended to deceive (such as “&lt;em&gt;paypal.com-myaccount-login-issuespayment-global.realbaddomain.com&lt;/em&gt;”) should immediately stand out, but we also need to be alert of other more insidious techniques!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Google’s quiz exemplifies, a phishing link could come in the form of an actual Google domain for example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;https://google.com/amp/gmail-account-activation.support/&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This would be a valid Google link redirecting to an hypothetical phishing site. Similarly, an email could also contain a valid Google link that will lead to a prompt requesting a malicious app to be enabled on our Gmail account. Ironically, even the domain of the quiz could be deceiving: what is withgoogle.com?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Essentially we are demanding individuals to not only be able to discern clearly forged domains from legitimate sites, but also to be aware of all the possible tricks to abuse existing functionality (such as OAuth&lt;sup id=&quot;a1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#f1&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; or redirects). Additionally, we are demanding them to be aware of what email addresses or message formats are commonly used by legitimate services at any point in time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is unattainable. If the burden relies so heavily on users, the underlying technology appears inadequate to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Without entering in the merit of mitigations such as two-factor authentication (which I discussed in the previous newsletter), or with other complications such as spoofing, we have identified enough booby traps already to likely dissuade most people from learning about online accounts security.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need more consistency across services. Consistency of procedures, language and available mitigations. And perhaps it is time to sacrifice some convenience and functionality in favor of a smaller attack surface.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;p.s.: As you might have noticed, I am making excessive use of the term “individuals”. I am purposefully trying to avoid “users”, which I generally don’t like. If you have any recommendations for more suitable words, I would very much appreciate them!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;f1&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;1: &lt;a href=&quot;https://duo.com/blog/gmail-oauth-phishing-goes-viral&quot;&gt;GMail OAuth Phishing Goes Viral&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#a1&quot;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
            <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
            <link>https://nex.sx//blog/2019/01/22/the-losing-battle-of-phishing-education.html</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://nex.sx//blog/2019/01/22/the-losing-battle-of-phishing-education.html</guid>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Phishing, Two-Factor Authentication and False Myths</title>
            <description>&lt;p&gt;Today we published a rather short report detailing a campaign of phishing attacks we monitored closely during the last year. You can find it here:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amnesty.org/en/latest/research/2018/12/when-best-practice-is-not-good-enough/&quot;&gt;https://www.amnesty.org/en/latest/research/2018/12/when-best-practice-is-not-good-enough/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this report we don’t get into attribution or victimology, but we provide what I believe to be an accessible read to describe how targeted phishing attacks are actually conducted by real state-sponsored attackers, in this case originating from a country in the Persian Gulf. While there are some interesting elements in the phishing of “secure email” services such as ProtonMail and Tutanota, what I found to be more fascinating and important to discuss at length, is the ability of this particular attacker to successfully bypass some forms of two-factor authentication.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note: although in this case two-step verification might be a more accurate term, for the sake of simplicity I am going to stick to two-factor authentication (2FA). However, if you are interested in understanding the purist differences you can find a good explanation here:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://lifehacker.com/the-difference-between-two-factor-and-two-step-authenti-1787159870&quot;&gt;https://lifehacker.com/the-difference-between-two-factor-and-two-step-authenti-1787159870&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Google offers several methods for two-factor authentication. By default it sends a verification code (normally made of 6 digits) via SMS to the registered phone number. The user would then be prompted to input the code they just received and continue with the login. Yahoo by default also provides the same login verification process. Both these services offer several other flavors of 2FA, including authenticator apps or push notifications (which consists in installing an app on the phone which will request you to manually approve a login by tapping a button, rather than copying a code).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we detailed in this report, the attackers have built a system cleverly designed to workaround at least the SMS based verification procedure. However, I believe the technique they used can be just as easily adapted to nearly every other form of verification including authenticator apps as well as push notifications. Essentially the attackers have built an “auto-pilot” software that automatically instruments a Google Chrome browser and directs it to the login pages of the service, such as Google or Yahoo, whenever a victim visits the phishing page and begines to provide account name and password. In the meantime, the software will in the background automatically enter the credentials to the legitimate service using the instrumented Chrome browser. If it notices that the service requires some additional information for verification purposes, such as the numerical code sent via SMS, the phishing page will simply display a clone of the original prompt and wait for the user to input the valid code that the service indeed sent to their phone at the request of the instrumented Chrome. If the victim, thinking of interacting with the original Google or Yahoo, enters the code in the phishing page, the software will copy it and send it to the original service it had open and complete the login process successfully.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They do this using a popular automation framework called Selenium, normally used for quality assurance and automated testing of web applications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While SMS code verification isn’t necessarily the strongest form of 2FA (and indeed, it should be generally avoided if only because SMS is an insecure protocol), I believe that with sufficient automation it is possible to bypass other flavors as well. For example, nothing prevents an attacker to just in the same way request valid codes from an authenticator app (such as Google Authenticator) and automatically use it with the instrumented browser. Or similarly, if in the background the instrumented Chrome is being required by the service to approve the login through a push notification, an attacker should be able to lure the victim into approving the login on their phone. If the attackers managed to lure the victim to enter their password, I don’t imagine an additional piece of information or action would be much harder to solicit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately this form of attack can be successful if the attackers build a sufficiently adaptable automation system to interact with the original services, combined with a frontend offering credible phishing pages to the victim. Unless the targeted online services implement heuristics or other mitigations against automation (such as CAPTCHAs), it might be hard defeat this. Worryingly, building such a phishing framework is not actually that complicated, and as a matter of fact we have observed other low-sophisticated state-sponsored attackers employing just the same techniques as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am very concerned about this. Particularly when it comes to individuals at risk and activist communities, I personally witness an alarmingly common misconception over the security promise these 2FA flavors offer. As a result, some of them have internalized a false sense of security which lead them to be significantly less cautious. For this we, as a community of technologists and security trainers, are most likely to be blamed due to the inadequacy of our security education programs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, this is not to say that two-factor authentication is a worthless effort, quite the contrary. ANY two-factor authentication is better than none, and there are ongoing developments in this space which will make these attacks less feasible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Currently, security keys supporting the U2F protocol (such as Yubikeys, Nitro keys, Solo keys, etc.) are the best available protection and I invite everyone to at least explore that option. The report provides some more elaborate considerations and recommendations about this, so I invite you to read it in full.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
            <pubDate>Thu, 20 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
            <link>https://nex.sx//blog/2018/12/20/phishing-2fa-and-false-myths.html</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://nex.sx//blog/2018/12/20/phishing-2fa-and-false-myths.html</guid>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>NSO Group and the Surveillance of Saudi Dissidents</title>
            <description>&lt;p&gt;NSO Group, the infamous Israeli surveillance company, has been under a lot of fire recently. If you remember, in August we published a report&lt;sup id=&quot;a1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#f1&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; in which we detailed how one of our staff members at Amnesty International (who was working on the issue of the Saudi women activists arrested&lt;sup id=&quot;a2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#f2&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;) was targeted using the mobile surveillance suite Pegasus, sold by NSO. In that report we also mentioned a Saudi human rights defender who we discovered also being targeted, whom identity we didn’t reveal at his request. Since then, he spontaneously decided to identify himself in the press as Yahya Assiri.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While at the time we discovered these attacks in early June they seemed like isolated events, over the months it became obvious that a larger campaign of surveillance was being conducted (most likely by the Saudi government) in a coordinated attempt to suppress dissent that culminated with the murder of Jamal Khashoggi.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On October 1st, right before the news of the murder, Citizen Lab discovered another Saudi dissident based in Canada, Omar Abdulaziz, was also targeted with NSO Group’s spyware&lt;sup id=&quot;a3&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#f3&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. In November, Forbes reported that yet another Saudi dissident, the YouTube comic and satirist Ghanem Almasarir, was also targeted with Pegasus&lt;sup id=&quot;a4&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#f4&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In October, we released a list&lt;sup id=&quot;a5&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#f5&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; of more than 600 domains used to deliver NSO Group’s exploits through SMS or WhatsApp messages. Recently we have also announced that we’re demanding for NSO Group’s export license to be revoked and we are considering legal action against the company&lt;sup id=&quot;a6&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#f6&quot;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Few days ago, Omar Abdulaziz also announced that he’s suing NSO Group in connection with the infection of his device, which he claims was purposefully targeted by the Saudi authorities to snoop on his communications with Khashoggi&lt;sup id=&quot;a7&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#f7&quot;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If all this wasn’t enough, Citizen Lab published yet another report detailing how Pegasus was used in Mexico to target journalists colleagues of a reporter who was gunned down in 2017, likely in connection with this investigations into the cartels&lt;sup id=&quot;a8&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#f8&quot;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have worked on plenty of investigations into surveillance companies, and uncovered numerous abuses of their products. However, the amount of cases where NSO Group’s Pegasus was found used to repress dissent and monitor reporters and human rights defenders is unprecedented. Why is that?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This piling number of abuses could very likely be a direct result of the company’s lack of proper human rights due diligence. According to an investigation by Haaretz, NSO Group indeed sold their products to Saudi Arabia for a wowing $55 million, apparently in defiance of the Israeli Ministry of Defence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, it could be that the efficacy and the sophistication of the attack suite that NSO Group provides, and the immense power that is derived, might in fact be an irresistible incentive for ruthless governments to use it even more so against dissidents, journalists and human rights defenders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While so far we have only observed attacks being delivered through SMS or WhatsApp messages requiring the victim to click on a link in order to activate the exploitation and infection, the investigation by Haaretz suggests that NSO Group might have sold Saudi Arabia their “0-click” solution as well. This would mean that Saudi Arabia, as well as any other government NSO Group might have sold this to, could have the ability to remotely compromise any iPhone without sending anything visible to the victims and without requiring them to click on any link. This could be theoretically possible if NSO Group would have knowledge of vulnerabilities in the radio components of the phone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Currently there is no evidence NSO Group or Saudi Arabia have access to such exploits. To the contrary, the fact that messages with “1-click” exploit links are being found around and used so widely rather suggests the opposite. However, if those claims are proved to be true, the effects of such a capability in the wrong hands could be catastrophic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With all attention and the mounting legal trouble, it is unclear what will happen with NSO Group. In the meantime, our investigations continue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are trying to identify other journalists and human rights defenders who might have also been similarly targeted with Pegasus. If you have any information to share, please do get in contact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can be found as @nex on Wire and @nex on Keybase, as well as via email:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;https://nex.sx/contacts/&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;f1&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;1: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amnesty.org/en/latest/research/2018/08/amnesty-international-among-targets-of-nso-powered-campaign/&quot;&gt;Amnesty International Among Targets of NSO-powered Campaign&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#a1&quot;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span id=&quot;f2&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;2: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/world/2018/may/19/saudi-arabia-womens-rights-activists-arrested-before-lifting-of-driving-ban&quot;&gt;Saudi Arabia: women’s rights activists arrested before lifting of driving ban&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#a2&quot;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span id=&quot;f3&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;3: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cbc.ca/news/technology/omar-abdulaziz-spyware-saudi-arabia-nso-citizen-lab-quebec-1.4845179&quot;&gt;A Quebecer spoke out against the Saudis - then learned he had spyware on his iPhone&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#a3&quot;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span id=&quot;f4&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;4: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.forbes.com/sites/thomasbrewster/2018/11/21/exclusive-saudi-dissidents-hit-with-stealth-iphone-spyware-before-khashoggis-murder/#5f7751dc2e8b&quot;&gt;Exclusive: Saudi Dissidents Hit With Stealth iPhone Spyware Before Khashoggi’s Murder&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#a4&quot;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span id=&quot;f5&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;5: &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/AmnestyTech/investigations/blob/master/2018-08-01_nso/indicators.csv&quot;&gt;investigations/indicators.csv&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#a5&quot;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span id=&quot;f6&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;6: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amnesty.org/en/latest/news/2018/11/israelroguenso-group-must-have-licence-revoked-over-controversial-surveillance-software/&quot;&gt;Israel: Rogue NSO Group must have licence revoked over controversial surveillance software&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#a6&quot;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span id=&quot;f7&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;7: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2018/12/02/world/middleeast/saudi-khashoggi-spyware-israel.html&quot;&gt;Israeli Software Helped Saudis Spy on Khashoggi, Lawsuit Says&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#a7&quot;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span id=&quot;f8&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;8: &lt;a href=&quot;https://citizenlab.ca/2018/11/mexican-journalists-investigating-cartels-targeted-nso-spyware-following-assassination-colleague/&quot;&gt;Reckless VI: Mexican Journalists Investigating Cartels Targeted with NSO Spyware Following Assassination of Colleague&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#a8&quot;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
            <pubDate>Wed, 05 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
            <link>https://nex.sx//blog/2018/12/05/nso-group-and-surveillance-of-saudi-dissidents.html</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://nex.sx//blog/2018/12/05/nso-group-and-surveillance-of-saudi-dissidents.html</guid>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Manipulation of Public Opinion</title>
            <description>&lt;p&gt;Manipulation of public opinion clearly isn’t anything new. It has traditionally been achieved by repeating over and over a specific message in the public and to the media to install a particular narrative that serves one’s interests. This commonly manifests with catchphrases which, just like commercial advertisement, are repeated endlessly until they become permanently ingrained in the public consciousness. We’ve seen it for example with the “blood on his hands” rhetoric being used against Snowden and Manning in the last years. We’re seeing it recently in the UK with “coalition of chaos” being used by the conservatives to refer to the opposition. And we’ve seen countless examples of that also by Trump during the 2016 campaign.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;The public is fundamentally a consumer of political advertisement.&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Social media has become an extension of this. Today’s Internet economic incentives foster an environment of clickbait and instant gratification, originally leveraged for online advertisement and moneymaking, but that it turns out is perfect too for catchphrase politics, particularly in a moment of resurgence of demonizing politics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With social media increasingly becoming a primary platform for the consumption of information, it also clearly has become a field where propaganda and misinformation campaigns play out. But the Internet doesn’t exist in a vacuum, it’s quite simply a reflection of society, with all good and bad that comes with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With much talk of fake news (which quite frankly, is a term that I believe should be abandoned, because it is imprecise and unhelpful for a constructive debate) and of social media bots, I think we’re seeing a concerning trend towards a techno-fatalism, that finds in technology a scapegoat for significant societal issues (as we’ve seen time and time again with the introduction in society of a new technology), and that as a result invokes some kind of techno-solutionism, which is just as problematic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are seeing some movements towards the over-regulation of content online. For example in Germany, where a law was passed that enforces fines of tens of millions of euros to companies who fail to enforce some appropriate and timely filtering of content and countering of “fake news”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are complex phenomena that require deep and dedicated study to fully understand. There is no solid indication yet of what is the measured impact (for example on elections) of false news and Twitter bots, and while they might very well have some, it is imperative that before implementing further laws and controls we have a good and documented view of what is the nature of this problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These issues need to be analyzed in the geographical and socio-political context in which they manifest. The impact of such phenomena will differ between countries that implement repressive policies with serious dangers involved in political manifestation, and say countries with a strong respect for the rule of law and human rights. These differences might warrant different reactions and countermeasures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;Firstly, it is reassuring to know that humans still lead the political debate.&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the matter of misinformation campaigns, Facebook recently stated for example that: “while we acknowledge the ongoing challenge of monitoring and guarding against information operations, the reach of known operations during the US election of 2016 was statistically very small compared to overall engagement on political issues.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A study by Stanford University comes to similar conclusions, and professor and co-author Matthew Gentzkow commented that “a reader of our study could very reasonably say, based on our set of facts, that it is unlikely that fake news swayed the election” and that “social media was an important but not dominant source of news in the run-up to the election”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In regards to the French elections, Oxford University published a paper that assessed the distribution of news over social media in the run-up to the first round and found that “the largest proportion of content being shared by Twitter users interested in French politics comes from professional news organizations. Information from political parties, government agencies and other experts is also being used. Still, 19.6 percent of the content being shared involves other kinds of political news and information. Yet the largest proportion of that content is not junk news but citizen-generated content”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And not only that, but that in regards to Twitter bots “by candidate, it appears that most of the candidates have roughly the same number of highly automated accounts generating traffic about them.”
 And yet this automated traffic amounted to roughly 7% of the total, according to the researchers at Oxford.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All this is to say that we need to step back a little and look at it with perspective in order to find appropriate and proportionate solutions that promote and respect the right to freedom of expression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A response driven by anxiety and panic is unlikely to be a constructive one and we don’t want to end up in a place where companies, instead of courts and the public opinion, are entitled to decide what is rightful content and what isn’t, and by extension we do not want to create regimes of over-censorship, because it is not by filtering that we solve bigotry and racism. Additionally, we might not realize that, while implementing certain restrictions or controls over some technology that might seem threatening to us, we might cause an unintended impact on the lives of others in other parts of the world. For example, a crack down on the right to anonymity online and enforcing service providers to police that, will necessarily mean for example that some human rights defenders in another country will not be able to do their work safely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That said, it is important that the public is well informed and it is not deceived. When we’ll get to the point where social media will be in fact the primary source of news, and by my reading it doesn’t seem to be there quite yet, the real answer to these issues will be education and media literacy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;Technology can’t be “trusted”, technology needs to be understood.&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we need to make sure that especially generations to come will be prepared to enter in their political life with the right understanding of how technology works, of how media and social media work and how they can be influenced, and to make sure they are taught the value of, and equipped with ways to actively seek diverse and accurate information.
 And that is not just in response to the issue of misinformation and propaganda, but really it is simply a requirement for nurturing open minds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are however some considerations that need to be asked to ensure technology and the Internet can contribute positively, rather than negatively, to society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Firstly, we need to re-think online advertisement, which besides being a toxic market that is corrosive to the right to privacy, it is also a key enabler of the twisted dynamics that I just spoke about. It is online advertisement after all that is the primary cause of clickbaiting, with all the consequences that it brings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly we need to engage the tech giants and require an opening of their systems for algorithmic decision making. We just can not rely on systems that select, prioritize and carry information that operate in ways that are cloaked by trade secrets. Even if those algorithmic decisions might not be an immediate issue now, they very likely will be in the future and, as we know, rolling back technologies that have been in place for years is just too hard, and we instead should make sure we build them with all the ethical and social considerations in mind from the very beginning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;This text is adapted from my speech at re:publica 2017 in conversation with Garry Kasparov.&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
            <pubDate>Wed, 24 May 2017 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
            <link>https://nex.sx//blog/2017/05/24/manipulation-public-opinion.html</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://nex.sx//blog/2017/05/24/manipulation-public-opinion.html</guid>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>On the Banality of Attacks and on Mindful Engineering</title>
            <description>&lt;p&gt;Over the years of my experience assisting journalists and dissidents with matters of computer security, and researching the nature of the threats they face, I learned that those who don’t have access to security solutions and do not operate in a managed environment, are often not best served by the consumer technology they are normally provided with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a recognizable difference between the design of certain consumer technology and some other. Mobile phones, for example, are increasingly provided with operating systems that are designed — for the most part, at least — around the interests of end-users. Other technology, like personal computer’s operating systems, seem to be often designed around the interests of the Enterprise sector instead. It really depends on what appears to be the primary target market for the producer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To me, this is signified by the fact that among the many — and I mean, really a lot of — attacks that I have observed targeting members of civil society, the use of exploits is a rare sight. Mind, not just zero-day exploits, but even just exploits at all. The large majority of attacks that I observe leverage tricks as infection vectors that are very simply (ab)using features that are exposed by the operating system or mainstream consumer software, and that seem to be mostly intended for enterprise users. Rather than a lack of sophistication on the part of the state-sponsored actors orchestrating these attacks, I believe this rather indicates a dire state of overall security controls.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are definitely tactical advantages in using tricks rather than exploitation. For example, abusing features exposed by operating systems like Microsoft Windows or by primary consumer applications like Microsoft Office, or Adobe Reader, requires way less situational awareness. Attackers do not need to know which architecture, build, or version of the particular software targets use, and as such there is no need to spend resources and time crafting attacks that must be reliable. This is particularly true when the target of an attacker is a diverse demographic that does not operate within an uniformed technology stack as it generally is in corporate and government environments. Additionally, while attackers often look for that one weak entry point to exploit in the operations of corporations or government institutions, the targeting of activist and dissident groups is often opportunistic — except, of course, of some individuals who are of particular interest — and attackers seek instead to just compromise as many people as possible. As a matter of fact, it is common to see the same spearphishing email being sent in carbon copy to dozen of individuals, even working for different organizations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For these reasons, targeting activists, journalists, and dissidents using tricks is very likely way less expensive than using exploits, and might in fact result in a higher success rate. Consequently, this is driving up the numbers of attacks we witness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most common vectors for spearphishing attacks that I’ve observed in the last year involved the abuse either of Microsoft Office Macros and Packager Shell Objects, or the abuse of PowerShell or Windows Script Host. With perhaps the exception of Macros for Excel, all the remaining tricks are powered by features that are generally useless to regular users, and are rather thought for the Enterprise sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For some of them, I can’t even think of any reasonable legitimate use. For example: why should one be able to embed Windows executables inside a PowerPoint title slide and automatically launch them through a custom animation? &lt;em&gt;(Insert here a dozen more implicit question and exclamation marks.)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I understand. A lot has to do with enabling system administrators and software developers to automate some of their tasks. Yes, I am sure that PowerShell is great at that. I am also sure it is great for facilitating incident response in corporate environments. However, please don’t make those default options (or in the case of PowerShell, for example, no option at all). Organizations can provision the configuration they prefer, end users instead have to stick with what they’re given. I am all for rich features and plenty of possibilities, but I am also for security by default, not by choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me now demystify some of the most common responses I get when similarly ranting about these particular issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;“There is Antivirus software, they detect all that”&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Firstly, no. Secondly, any security design that relies on the efficacy of third party products that your user must discover and acquire is a ridiculous one.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;“Users should learn not to click on unsolicited links and attachments”&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Links and attachments are supposed to be clicked. It’s the whole point. If you expect users to be able to discriminate naturally between a legitimate email and a malicious one, you are detached from the reality of real world attacks. Attackers commonly befriend victims, impersonate their relatives and co-workers, and create all the pre-conditions to make the attack as credible as possible.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;“Users are warned when they are about to execute something dangerous”&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;div style=&quot;float: left;padding-right: 20px;padding-bottom: 5px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/blog/20170111/warning.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;That’s not always the case, but it is for some applications. However, it is also clear that vague, undescriptive warnings — like the one displayed on the side — are not enough. For example, in the case of some targeted attacks against dissidents in Iran my co-conspirator Collin and I have documented last year, the malware was delivered through malicious PowerPoint presentations that embedded multiple copies of the same executable in the title slide and launched it in the same way I described earlier. Why multiple copies? Because while at the first, or second, or third security warning dialog from Microsoft Office the victim might not allow the payload to execute, they most likely will at the fourth or fifth. We formalized this technique as Security Bypass by Annoyance.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;“Even if you disable one feature or another, there’s so many ways to compromise someone”&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;True. It still doesn’t mean however that we should leave all doors open. Reducing the number of possible attack points allows us to deal and watch for the fewer remaining ones more efficiently.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To this effect, my dear friend emdel and I at Security Without Borders have started aggregating tips &amp;amp; tricks to disable some of these most problematic features in a little experimental utility that is being assembled here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, I invite software producers — especially those who provide highly popular consumer applications — to stay informed on how some of their choices are being regularly abused, to stop blaming users, and to start practicing more mindful engineering.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
            <pubDate>Wed, 11 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
            <link>https://nex.sx//blog/2017/01/11/on-banality-of-attacks.html</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://nex.sx//blog/2017/01/11/on-banality-of-attacks.html</guid>
        </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>
