<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>Nex</title>
        <description>The personal website of Claudio Guarnieri, alias Nex.
</description>
        <link>https://nex.sx</link>
        <atom:link href="https://nex.sx/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
        
        <item>
            <title>Exodus: How the Discovery of a Malware Revealed a Spy Scandal in Italy</title>
            <description>&lt;p&gt;On Friday 29th Security Without Borders in collaboration with Motherboard published a new investigation into a previously unknown surveillance vendor from Italy called eSurv.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://securitywithoutborders.org/blog/2019/03/29/exodus.html&quot;&gt;https://securitywithoutborders.org/blog/2019/03/29/exodus.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This company, which purported to only be a surveillance cameras manufacturer, in reality has been producing intrusion software (spyware) since at least 2016. We dubbed this spyware “Exodus” after a domain name used as Command &amp;amp; Control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://motherboard.vice.com/en_us/article/43z93g/hackers-hid-android-malware-in-google-play-store-exodus-esurv&quot;&gt;https://motherboard.vice.com/en_us/article/43z93g/hackers-hid-android-malware-in-google-play-store-exodus-esurv&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As originally noted by Motherboard through publicly available documents, and as now confirmed by public prosecutor’s offices, this software was in use by law enforcement all over Italy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What made this software particularly worrying for us was, firstly, that it was widely distributed through the Google Play Store and publicly accessible for anybody to install. As a matter of fact, hundreds of installations were registered across 25 different copies of the spyware. Secondly, the spyware is able to collect much more information than what is normally mandated by law in Italy. Thirdly, the spyware would establish  unencrypted reverse shells to the Command &amp;amp; Control, that could be prone to man-in-the-middle attacks. Lastly, and even more worryingly in my mind, it would enable terminal access to the device by simply connecting to various fixed TCP port numbers, effectively leaving the phone exposed to further compromise or data tampering by anybody who would share the same network (such as a public Wi-Fi, or potentially even the same cellular network).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This story gained significant attention on Italian press and received coverage on all major newspapers, online and print, as well as on prime time television news on Saturday. While the initial press coverage wasn’t particularly accurate, it opened up to some interesting and unexpected developments that are still unfolding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The prosecutor of Napoli informed the press that an investigation was active on the company and that few days prior to our publication a judge issued a seizure warrant for eSurv and its assets, as well as another company, STM s.r.l.&lt;sup id=&quot;a1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#f1&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Italian press reports that STM s.r.l. had numerous contracts with public prosecutor’s offices across Italy to setup and maintain the Exodus system they purchased from eSurv. The prosecutor’s office of Benevento recently realized, during yet another apparent malfunction, that the Exodus spyware in their use wasn’t exfiltrating and storing data on the local server in the premises of the office (as mandated by Italian law), but on Amazon cloud instances instead. As a matter of fact, the press reports, the server provided to the public prosecutor’s office wasn’t even equipped with an Operating System, and contained no data at all. Essentially it was an empty box. Additionally, it appears that interception data from invesigations by several other public prosecutor’s offices was stored on this same Amazon instance, and that the companies maintained privileged access.&lt;sup id=&quot;a2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#f2&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is wild.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Exodus servers are being analyzed and people are being investigated. It is unclear currently what was the purpose and who was the operator of the malicious apps we discovered on the Play Store and how many of the hundreds of victims were intended and how many were accidental.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More recent reports are now suggesting that the story might go deeper and darker than originally anticipated. The press is currently suggesting that illegal spying might have been operated on behalf of unknown entities&lt;sup id=&quot;a3&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#f3&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; and that this investigation is crossing with separate investigations dealing with corruption in Calabria&lt;sup id=&quot;a4&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#f4&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By all accounts, it seems that this story is still unfolding. More information will likely follow as more details from the investigations will come to light.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hopefully, this case will reinvigorate a much needed debate on the nature of lawful interception intrusion software and the Wild West that is the industry behind it. In these years we have mostly debated on how to properly export these technologies out of Europe, but if anything, this case should highlight the very serious legal, technical, and constitutional issues raised by its current use here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;f1&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;1: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ilfattoquotidiano.it/2019/04/01/exodus-4-indagati-a-napoli-intercettati-illegalmente-centinaia-di-italiani-dati-giudiziari-salvati-su-un-cloud-amazon/5078359/&quot;&gt;Exodus, 4 indagati a Napoli. Intercettati illegalmente centinaia di italiani: “Dati giudiziari salvati su un cloud Amazon” - Il Fatto Quotidiano&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span id=&quot;f2&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;2: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ilfattoquotidiano.it/2019/04/02/benevento-software-spia-farlocchi-e-server-giudiziari-vuoti-sui-cloud-amazon-anche-le-intercettazioni-di-altre-procure/5079009/&quot;&gt;Benevento, software spia farlocchi e server giudiziari vuoti: sui cloud Amazon anche le intercettazioni di altre procure - Il Fatto Quotidiano&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span id=&quot;f3&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;3: &lt;a href=&quot;https://roma.corriere.it/notizie/cronaca/19_aprile_01/sospetto-dossieraggi-ricatti-il-software-spia-telefonini-c2347232-54b6-11e9-a9e2-a0d1446d1611.shtml&quot;&gt;Il sospetto di dossieraggi e ricatti con il software spia nei telefonini - Corriere.it&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span id=&quot;f4&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;4: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.corrieredellacalabria.it/regione/cosenza/item/181508-magistrati-e-investigatori-gli-amici-calabresi-del-poliziotto-della-spy-story/&quot;&gt;Magistrati e investigatori, gli amici calabresi del poliziotto della “spy story” - Corriere della Calabria&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
            <pubDate>Thu, 04 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
            <link>https://nex.sx//blog/2019/04/04/exodus-spy-scandal-italy.html</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://nex.sx//blog/2019/04/04/exodus-spy-scandal-italy.html</guid>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Phishing Attacks Using Third-Party Applications Against Egyptian Civil Society Organizations</title>
            <description>&lt;p&gt;I am aware that most of my recent newsletters dealt with the issue of account security and phishing, but I have one more story on this to share with you. I suppose this is indicative of the sad nature of the digital (in)security we face today. I promise, in the newsletters to come I will cover other topics as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yesterday, we published a short blog post warning of an ongoing campaign of phishing attacks targeting human rights defenders and NGOs from Egypt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amnesty.org/en/latest/research/2019/03/phishing-attacks-using-third-party-applications-against-egyptian-civil-society-organizations/&quot;&gt;https://www.amnesty.org/en/latest/research/2019/03/phishing-attacks-using-third-party-applications-against-egyptian-civil-society-organizations/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To quote directly from the report:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Since January 2019 several human rights defenders and civil society organizations from Egypt started forwarding dozens of suspicious emails to Amnesty International. Through the course of our investigation we discovered that these emails were attempts to access the email accounts of their targets through a particularly insidious form of phishing known as OAuth Phishing (which we explain in detail below). We estimate the total number of targeted individuals to be in the order of several hundreds.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“These coincided with a number of important events that took place in the country. In the run-up to the eighth anniversary of Egypt’s 25 January uprising, which ended with the removal of former president Hosni Mubarak, after 30 years in power, we recorded 11 phishing attacks against NGOs and media collectives. We saw another burst of attacks during French President Emmanuel Macron’s visit to Cairo to meet with President Abdelfatah al-Sisi on 28 and 29 January. The attacks peaked on 29 January, the day that President Macron met with human rights defenders from four prominent Egyptian NGOs. Later, in the first week of February, several media organizations were targeted as part of this campaign of digital attacks; they were reporting on the process of amending the Egyptian Constitution that the parliament had just officially started.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OAuth Phishing is an insidious phishing technique that is not very common, and consequently not as widely known to individuals at risk as the more traditional forms of phishing. Additionally, security education material rarely includes mentions of OAuth Phishing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Essentially, OAuth Phishing relies on a feature that is commonly available with many email providers (such as Google, Yahoo, Hotmail and Outlook) that allows people to grant third-party applications access to their accounts. Legitimate third-party applications could be designed to, for example, extract invitations or flight and hotel bookings from the email inbox and add them to an external calendar application.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Attackers can abuse this feature and create malicious third-party applications that are masqueraded as legitimate while in reality their purpose is to steal the emails from the victim.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the blog post we provide additional details and visuals explaining how this attack works and how to mitigate against it. Unfortunately, because this form of phishing does not rely on creating and distributing a fake login prompt for a legitimate service, but abuses the service directly, the only prevention is to be alert and suspicious of third-party applications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we highlight in the blog post, the targets of this latest campaign in Egypt significantly overlap with the targets of a similar phishing campaign discovered two years ago. At the time, the attackers set up the typical Google login clones and lured targets into giving away their credentials. Since then, human rights defenders and NGOs have equipped themselves with two-factor authentication solutions that mitigated that form of phishing. Now, the attackers have clearly adapted and the use of OAuth Phishing seems like a direct response to the better security practices that have been adopted by their targets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Attackers are agile in their tactics, we need to be as agile in our defenses.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
            <pubDate>Fri, 08 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
            <link>https://nex.sx//blog/2019/03/08/phishing-attacks-against-egyptian-civil-society.html</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://nex.sx//blog/2019/03/08/phishing-attacks-against-egyptian-civil-society.html</guid>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>The Death of The Exploit</title>
            <description>&lt;p&gt;Matt Miller, from Microsoft Security Response Center, delivered a very interesting presentation at the Bluehat conference few days ago titled “Trends, challenges, and strategic shifts in the software vulnerability mitigation landscape”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this presentation Matt, who is otherwise known as “skape” and is recognized for his many years of work on exploit research and his contributions to the Metasploit project, provided a very interesting overview of the progress made over the last decade on tackling software vulnerabilities. I very much recommending reading the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/Microsoft/MSRC-Security-Research/blob/master/presentations/2019_02_BlueHatIL/2019_&quot;&gt;slides&lt;/a&gt; and I hope a video recording will be made available soon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are several takeaways from this presentation, and those I found most relevant are:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;1) While the amount of known software vulnerabilities reported every year follows an increasing trajectory, the percentage of those that are actually exploited in the wild is decreasing.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This highlights an interesting discrepancy which is hard to recognize for those who do not have access to telemetry such as Microsoft’s: while software vulnerabilities appear to be piling up like never before, attackers are leveraging fewer. This is an interesting trend and while I can imagine a variety of factors that might be influencing this shift, I would be interested in hearing more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;2) Increasingly more often, software vulnerabilities are found to be exploited for the first time as 0days, rather than after a patch is released.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Publicly available exploits are becoming less effective, possibly because of more dedicated update mechanisms employed by recent versions of Windows, and less reliable, thanks to the various mitigation techniques introduced in the last years. Leveraging a patched vulnerability now is most likely to be unsuccessful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, we need to wary of generalizations. Especially in countries with economic difficulties and even more so in countries subjected to embargoes, the availability of most recent hardware and software might be limited, particularly at the cost of individuals at risk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;3) Exploit mitigations have had a significant impact, and we might see a day not too far away where software vulnerabilities are not as much of a concern anymore.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Essentially, things are getting better. With the exception of WannaCry, mass-spreading threats have nearly disappeared and so has the pandemic exploitation of browsers and plugins and of productivity suites.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve been making similar observations in my monitoring of state-sponsored campaigns. While some years ago the largest majority of attacks were almost expected to make use of an Adobe Reader or Office exploit (ah, the good old CVE-2012-0158 days!) now any exploit at all is a rare sight for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the last couple of years I have been doing the exercise of looking back at all disclosed campaigns of targeted attacks against civil society from the previous year and try to derive some patterns and trends. With the exception of some high profile cases, such as those of NSO Group, the cases in which any exploit at all (0day or not) was used are near zero.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Instead, way more predominant is the abuse of certain Windows and Office features that are primarily intended for enterprises but are also a perfect attack surface for end users (such as Macros, OLE, DDE, PowerShell, etc.) and reflect a &lt;a href=&quot;https://nex.sx/blog/2017/01/11/on-banality-of-attacks.html&quot;&gt;lack of care for the needs of individuals at risk&lt;/a&gt;. In addition, more recently credentials phishing seems to be making a &lt;a href=&quot;https://nex.sx/blog/2018/12/20/phishing-2fa-and-false-myths.html&quot;&gt;strong return&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a matter of fact, I believe we are currently witnessing a bigger investment in improving credential phishing frameworks and tactics than in developing spyware. The spyware we observe is generally rudimentary and, while I have no solid data to back this up, I believe spyware’s return of investment is getting comparatively lower than that of phishing. The infection rate is quite likely significantly decreasing and at no discount of operational costs. Phishing instead largely remains an unsolved problem and it is quantitatively the most common threat we observe these days. Although I very wildly estimate a success rate generally below 10%, it’s an attack that is cheap to develop and operate and is reusable almost indefinitely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Getting back to software vulnerabilities and exploits, Matt writes in his presentation that Microsoft’s strategy against them is turning from “increasing cost &amp;amp; difficulty” to “getting to done”. It’s comforting to think we might eventually be “done” with exploits, but if we learned anything out of decades of cybersecurity is that the death of the exploit might just be the birth of something new.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
            <pubDate>Wed, 13 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
            <link>https://nex.sx//blog/2019/02/13/the-death-of-the-exploit.html</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://nex.sx//blog/2019/02/13/the-death-of-the-exploit.html</guid>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>The Losing Battle of Phishing Education</title>
            <description>&lt;p&gt;Today Google Jigsaw launched a new resource self-descriptively called Phishing Quiz. I generally applaud these efforts and I myself often recur to quizzes in my occasional trainings. This one is well designed and straightforward to use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://phishingquiz.withgoogle.com/&quot;&gt;https://phishingquiz.withgoogle.com/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The declared purpose of these quizzes is to enable potential at-risk individuals to train their eyes in spotting suspicious elements in email messages and web pages. For me, the purpose is rather to highlight the difficulty in recognizing well-crafted phishing attacks, and the numerous design inconsistencies across online service providers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Google’s quiz perfectly highlights many of these inconsistencies, and I invite you to try it for yourself. I did the same and at the end of it I tried to anticipate how an individual approaching this subject for the first time might leave confused.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Training individuals to detect phishing attacks through visual references is hard, because those don’t follow a logic shared across platforms and because they change occasionally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;[SPOILER ALERT: I am going to reference certain results from the Google Phishing Quiz, so do not read further if you don’t want any anticipations.]&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this quiz the primary two key visual elements the exercises are based upon are the email sender’s address and the links contained in the body of the message. Ideally, through this, individuals should identify patterns and construct a mental model to apply to any similar real-case scenario. However, we immediately see inconsistencies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In one exercise we are suggested that an email is in fact legitimate because, along with the validity of a contained link, the sender’s email address contain the domain @dropboxmail.com, which is an actual domain in use by Dropbox instead of the more intuitive @dropbox.com. At the same time, however, a different exercise alerts us that an email sender with @google.support is malicious because the domain is not in use by Google.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps an agreement among service providers to all adopt a similar scheme would be beneficial. For example, instead of using various domain names, all should stick to their primary domain for email communications, e.g. &lt;em&gt;noreply@dropbox.com&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;noreply@google.com&lt;/em&gt; instead of &lt;em&gt;dropboxmail.com&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;googlemail.com&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When it comes to links contained in the body of email messages we could expect similar confusion. Forged domains intended to deceive (such as “&lt;em&gt;paypal.com-myaccount-login-issuespayment-global.realbaddomain.com&lt;/em&gt;”) should immediately stand out, but we also need to be alert of other more insidious techniques!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Google’s quiz exemplifies, a phishing link could come in the form of an actual Google domain for example:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;https://google.com/amp/gmail-account-activation.support/&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This would be a valid Google link redirecting to an hypothetical phishing site. Similarly, an email could also contain a valid Google link that will lead to a prompt requesting a malicious app to be enabled on our Gmail account. Ironically, even the domain of the quiz could be deceiving: what is withgoogle.com?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Essentially we are demanding individuals to not only be able to discern clearly forged domains from legitimate sites, but also to be aware of all the possible tricks to abuse existing functionality (such as OAuth&lt;sup id=&quot;a1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#f1&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; or redirects). Additionally, we are demanding them to be aware of what email addresses or message formats are commonly used by legitimate services at any point in time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is unattainable. If the burden relies so heavily on users, the underlying technology appears inadequate to me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Without entering in the merit of mitigations such as two-factor authentication (which I discussed in the previous newsletter), or with other complications such as spoofing, we have identified enough booby traps already to likely dissuade most people from learning about online accounts security.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need more consistency across services. Consistency of procedures, language and available mitigations. And perhaps it is time to sacrifice some convenience and functionality in favor of a smaller attack surface.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;p.s.: As you might have noticed, I am making excessive use of the term “individuals”. I am purposefully trying to avoid “users”, which I generally don’t like. If you have any recommendations for more suitable words, I would very much appreciate them!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;f1&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;1: &lt;a href=&quot;https://duo.com/blog/gmail-oauth-phishing-goes-viral&quot;&gt;GMail OAuth Phishing Goes Viral&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#a1&quot;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
            <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
            <link>https://nex.sx//blog/2019/01/22/the-losing-battle-of-phishing-education.html</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://nex.sx//blog/2019/01/22/the-losing-battle-of-phishing-education.html</guid>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Phishing, Two-Factor Authentication and False Myths</title>
            <description>&lt;p&gt;Today we published a rather short report detailing a campaign of phishing attacks we monitored closely during the last year. You can find it here:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amnesty.org/en/latest/research/2018/12/when-best-practice-is-not-good-enough/&quot;&gt;https://www.amnesty.org/en/latest/research/2018/12/when-best-practice-is-not-good-enough/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this report we don’t get into attribution or victimology, but we provide what I believe to be an accessible read to describe how targeted phishing attacks are actually conducted by real state-sponsored attackers, in this case originating from a country in the Persian Gulf. While there are some interesting elements in the phishing of “secure email” services such as ProtonMail and Tutanota, what I found to be more fascinating and important to discuss at length, is the ability of this particular attacker to successfully bypass some forms of two-factor authentication.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Note: although in this case two-step verification might be a more accurate term, for the sake of simplicity I am going to stick to two-factor authentication (2FA). However, if you are interested in understanding the purist differences you can find a good explanation here:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://lifehacker.com/the-difference-between-two-factor-and-two-step-authenti-1787159870&quot;&gt;https://lifehacker.com/the-difference-between-two-factor-and-two-step-authenti-1787159870&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Google offers several methods for two-factor authentication. By default it sends a verification code (normally made of 6 digits) via SMS to the registered phone number. The user would then be prompted to input the code they just received and continue with the login. Yahoo by default also provides the same login verification process. Both these services offer several other flavors of 2FA, including authenticator apps or push notifications (which consists in installing an app on the phone which will request you to manually approve a login by tapping a button, rather than copying a code).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we detailed in this report, the attackers have built a system cleverly designed to workaround at least the SMS based verification procedure. However, I believe the technique they used can be just as easily adapted to nearly every other form of verification including authenticator apps as well as push notifications. Essentially the attackers have built an “auto-pilot” software that automatically instruments a Google Chrome browser and directs it to the login pages of the service, such as Google or Yahoo, whenever a victim visits the phishing page and begines to provide account name and password. In the meantime, the software will in the background automatically enter the credentials to the legitimate service using the instrumented Chrome browser. If it notices that the service requires some additional information for verification purposes, such as the numerical code sent via SMS, the phishing page will simply display a clone of the original prompt and wait for the user to input the valid code that the service indeed sent to their phone at the request of the instrumented Chrome. If the victim, thinking of interacting with the original Google or Yahoo, enters the code in the phishing page, the software will copy it and send it to the original service it had open and complete the login process successfully.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They do this using a popular automation framework called Selenium, normally used for quality assurance and automated testing of web applications.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While SMS code verification isn’t necessarily the strongest form of 2FA (and indeed, it should be generally avoided if only because SMS is an insecure protocol), I believe that with sufficient automation it is possible to bypass other flavors as well. For example, nothing prevents an attacker to just in the same way request valid codes from an authenticator app (such as Google Authenticator) and automatically use it with the instrumented browser. Or similarly, if in the background the instrumented Chrome is being required by the service to approve the login through a push notification, an attacker should be able to lure the victim into approving the login on their phone. If the attackers managed to lure the victim to enter their password, I don’t imagine an additional piece of information or action would be much harder to solicit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately this form of attack can be successful if the attackers build a sufficiently adaptable automation system to interact with the original services, combined with a frontend offering credible phishing pages to the victim. Unless the targeted online services implement heuristics or other mitigations against automation (such as CAPTCHAs), it might be hard defeat this. Worryingly, building such a phishing framework is not actually that complicated, and as a matter of fact we have observed other low-sophisticated state-sponsored attackers employing just the same techniques as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am very concerned about this. Particularly when it comes to individuals at risk and activist communities, I personally witness an alarmingly common misconception over the security promise these 2FA flavors offer. As a result, some of them have internalized a false sense of security which lead them to be significantly less cautious. For this we, as a community of technologists and security trainers, are most likely to be blamed due to the inadequacy of our security education programs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, this is not to say that two-factor authentication is a worthless effort, quite the contrary. ANY two-factor authentication is better than none, and there are ongoing developments in this space which will make these attacks less feasible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Currently, security keys supporting the U2F protocol (such as Yubikeys, Nitro keys, Solo keys, etc.) are the best available protection and I invite everyone to at least explore that option. The report provides some more elaborate considerations and recommendations about this, so I invite you to read it in full.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
            <pubDate>Thu, 20 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
            <link>https://nex.sx//blog/2018/12/20/phishing-2fa-and-false-myths.html</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://nex.sx//blog/2018/12/20/phishing-2fa-and-false-myths.html</guid>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>NSO Group and the Surveillance of Saudi Dissidents</title>
            <description>&lt;p&gt;NSO Group, the infamous Israeli surveillance company, has been under a lot of fire recently. If you remember, in August we published a report&lt;sup id=&quot;a1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#f1&quot;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; in which we detailed how one of our staff members at Amnesty International (who was working on the issue of the Saudi women activists arrested&lt;sup id=&quot;a2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#f2&quot;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;) was targeted using the mobile surveillance suite Pegasus, sold by NSO. In that report we also mentioned a Saudi human rights defender who we discovered also being targeted, whom identity we didn’t reveal at his request. Since then, he spontaneously decided to identify himself in the press as Yahya Assiri.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While at the time we discovered these attacks in early June they seemed like isolated events, over the months it became obvious that a larger campaign of surveillance was being conducted (most likely by the Saudi government) in a coordinated attempt to suppress dissent that culminated with the murder of Jamal Khashoggi.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On October 1st, right before the news of the murder, Citizen Lab discovered another Saudi dissident based in Canada, Omar Abdulaziz, was also targeted with NSO Group’s spyware&lt;sup id=&quot;a3&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#f3&quot;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. In November, Forbes reported that yet another Saudi dissident, the YouTube comic and satirist Ghanem Almasarir, was also targeted with Pegasus&lt;sup id=&quot;a4&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#f4&quot;&gt;4&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In October, we released a list&lt;sup id=&quot;a5&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#f5&quot;&gt;5&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; of more than 600 domains used to deliver NSO Group’s exploits through SMS or WhatsApp messages. Recently we have also announced that we’re demanding for NSO Group’s export license to be revoked and we are considering legal action against the company&lt;sup id=&quot;a6&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#f6&quot;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. Few days ago, Omar Abdulaziz also announced that he’s suing NSO Group in connection with the infection of his device, which he claims was purposefully targeted by the Saudi authorities to snoop on his communications with Khashoggi&lt;sup id=&quot;a7&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#f7&quot;&gt;7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If all this wasn’t enough, Citizen Lab published yet another report detailing how Pegasus was used in Mexico to target journalists colleagues of a reporter who was gunned down in 2017, likely in connection with this investigations into the cartels&lt;sup id=&quot;a8&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#f8&quot;&gt;8&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have worked on plenty of investigations into surveillance companies, and uncovered numerous abuses of their products. However, the amount of cases where NSO Group’s Pegasus was found used to repress dissent and monitor reporters and human rights defenders is unprecedented. Why is that?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This piling number of abuses could very likely be a direct result of the company’s lack of proper human rights due diligence. According to an investigation by Haaretz, NSO Group indeed sold their products to Saudi Arabia for a wowing $55 million, apparently in defiance of the Israeli Ministry of Defence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, it could be that the efficacy and the sophistication of the attack suite that NSO Group provides, and the immense power that is derived, might in fact be an irresistible incentive for ruthless governments to use it even more so against dissidents, journalists and human rights defenders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While so far we have only observed attacks being delivered through SMS or WhatsApp messages requiring the victim to click on a link in order to activate the exploitation and infection, the investigation by Haaretz suggests that NSO Group might have sold Saudi Arabia their “0-click” solution as well. This would mean that Saudi Arabia, as well as any other government NSO Group might have sold this to, could have the ability to remotely compromise any iPhone without sending anything visible to the victims and without requiring them to click on any link. This could be theoretically possible if NSO Group would have knowledge of vulnerabilities in the radio components of the phone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Currently there is no evidence NSO Group or Saudi Arabia have access to such exploits. To the contrary, the fact that messages with “1-click” exploit links are being found around and used so widely rather suggests the opposite. However, if those claims are proved to be true, the effects of such a capability in the wrong hands could be catastrophic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With all attention and the mounting legal trouble, it is unclear what will happen with NSO Group. In the meantime, our investigations continue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are trying to identify other journalists and human rights defenders who might have also been similarly targeted with Pegasus. If you have any information to share, please do get in contact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can be found as @nex on Wire and @nex on Keybase, as well as via email:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;https://nex.sx/contacts/&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;f1&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;1: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amnesty.org/en/latest/research/2018/08/amnesty-international-among-targets-of-nso-powered-campaign/&quot;&gt;Amnesty International Among Targets of NSO-powered Campaign&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#a1&quot;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span id=&quot;f2&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;2: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/world/2018/may/19/saudi-arabia-womens-rights-activists-arrested-before-lifting-of-driving-ban&quot;&gt;Saudi Arabia: women’s rights activists arrested before lifting of driving ban&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#a2&quot;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span id=&quot;f3&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;3: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cbc.ca/news/technology/omar-abdulaziz-spyware-saudi-arabia-nso-citizen-lab-quebec-1.4845179&quot;&gt;A Quebecer spoke out against the Saudis - then learned he had spyware on his iPhone&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#a3&quot;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span id=&quot;f4&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;4: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.forbes.com/sites/thomasbrewster/2018/11/21/exclusive-saudi-dissidents-hit-with-stealth-iphone-spyware-before-khashoggis-murder/#5f7751dc2e8b&quot;&gt;Exclusive: Saudi Dissidents Hit With Stealth iPhone Spyware Before Khashoggi’s Murder&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#a4&quot;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span id=&quot;f5&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;5: &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/AmnestyTech/investigations/blob/master/2018-08-01_nso/indicators.csv&quot;&gt;investigations/indicators.csv&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#a5&quot;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span id=&quot;f6&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;6: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.amnesty.org/en/latest/news/2018/11/israelroguenso-group-must-have-licence-revoked-over-controversial-surveillance-software/&quot;&gt;Israel: Rogue NSO Group must have licence revoked over controversial surveillance software&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#a6&quot;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span id=&quot;f7&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;7: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2018/12/02/world/middleeast/saudi-khashoggi-spyware-israel.html&quot;&gt;Israeli Software Helped Saudis Spy on Khashoggi, Lawsuit Says&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#a7&quot;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;span id=&quot;f8&quot;&gt;&lt;/span&gt;8: &lt;a href=&quot;https://citizenlab.ca/2018/11/mexican-journalists-investigating-cartels-targeted-nso-spyware-following-assassination-colleague/&quot;&gt;Reckless VI: Mexican Journalists Investigating Cartels Targeted with NSO Spyware Following Assassination of Colleague&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#a8&quot;&gt;↩&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
            <pubDate>Wed, 05 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
            <link>https://nex.sx//blog/2018/12/05/nso-group-and-surveillance-of-saudi-dissidents.html</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://nex.sx//blog/2018/12/05/nso-group-and-surveillance-of-saudi-dissidents.html</guid>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Manipulation of Public Opinion</title>
            <description>&lt;p&gt;Manipulation of public opinion clearly isn’t anything new. It has traditionally been achieved by repeating over and over a specific message in the public and to the media to install a particular narrative that serves one’s interests. This commonly manifests with catchphrases which, just like commercial advertisement, are repeated endlessly until they become permanently ingrained in the public consciousness. We’ve seen it for example with the “blood on his hands” rhetoric being used against Snowden and Manning in the last years. We’re seeing it recently in the UK with “coalition of chaos” being used by the conservatives to refer to the opposition. And we’ve seen countless examples of that also by Trump during the 2016 campaign.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;The public is fundamentally a consumer of political advertisement.&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Social media has become an extension of this. Today’s Internet economic incentives foster an environment of clickbait and instant gratification, originally leveraged for online advertisement and moneymaking, but that it turns out is perfect too for catchphrase politics, particularly in a moment of resurgence of demonizing politics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With social media increasingly becoming a primary platform for the consumption of information, it also clearly has become a field where propaganda and misinformation campaigns play out. But the Internet doesn’t exist in a vacuum, it’s quite simply a reflection of society, with all good and bad that comes with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With much talk of fake news (which quite frankly, is a term that I believe should be abandoned, because it is imprecise and unhelpful for a constructive debate) and of social media bots, I think we’re seeing a concerning trend towards a techno-fatalism, that finds in technology a scapegoat for significant societal issues (as we’ve seen time and time again with the introduction in society of a new technology), and that as a result invokes some kind of techno-solutionism, which is just as problematic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are seeing some movements towards the over-regulation of content online. For example in Germany, where a law was passed that enforces fines of tens of millions of euros to companies who fail to enforce some appropriate and timely filtering of content and countering of “fake news”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are complex phenomena that require deep and dedicated study to fully understand. There is no solid indication yet of what is the measured impact (for example on elections) of false news and Twitter bots, and while they might very well have some, it is imperative that before implementing further laws and controls we have a good and documented view of what is the nature of this problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These issues need to be analyzed in the geographical and socio-political context in which they manifest. The impact of such phenomena will differ between countries that implement repressive policies with serious dangers involved in political manifestation, and say countries with a strong respect for the rule of law and human rights. These differences might warrant different reactions and countermeasures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;Firstly, it is reassuring to know that humans still lead the political debate.&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the matter of misinformation campaigns, Facebook recently stated for example that: “while we acknowledge the ongoing challenge of monitoring and guarding against information operations, the reach of known operations during the US election of 2016 was statistically very small compared to overall engagement on political issues.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A study by Stanford University comes to similar conclusions, and professor and co-author Matthew Gentzkow commented that “a reader of our study could very reasonably say, based on our set of facts, that it is unlikely that fake news swayed the election” and that “social media was an important but not dominant source of news in the run-up to the election”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In regards to the French elections, Oxford University published a paper that assessed the distribution of news over social media in the run-up to the first round and found that “the largest proportion of content being shared by Twitter users interested in French politics comes from professional news organizations. Information from political parties, government agencies and other experts is also being used. Still, 19.6 percent of the content being shared involves other kinds of political news and information. Yet the largest proportion of that content is not junk news but citizen-generated content”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And not only that, but that in regards to Twitter bots “by candidate, it appears that most of the candidates have roughly the same number of highly automated accounts generating traffic about them.”
 And yet this automated traffic amounted to roughly 7% of the total, according to the researchers at Oxford.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All this is to say that we need to step back a little and look at it with perspective in order to find appropriate and proportionate solutions that promote and respect the right to freedom of expression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A response driven by anxiety and panic is unlikely to be a constructive one and we don’t want to end up in a place where companies, instead of courts and the public opinion, are entitled to decide what is rightful content and what isn’t, and by extension we do not want to create regimes of over-censorship, because it is not by filtering that we solve bigotry and racism. Additionally, we might not realize that, while implementing certain restrictions or controls over some technology that might seem threatening to us, we might cause an unintended impact on the lives of others in other parts of the world. For example, a crack down on the right to anonymity online and enforcing service providers to police that, will necessarily mean for example that some human rights defenders in another country will not be able to do their work safely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That said, it is important that the public is well informed and it is not deceived. When we’ll get to the point where social media will be in fact the primary source of news, and by my reading it doesn’t seem to be there quite yet, the real answer to these issues will be education and media literacy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;Technology can’t be “trusted”, technology needs to be understood.&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we need to make sure that especially generations to come will be prepared to enter in their political life with the right understanding of how technology works, of how media and social media work and how they can be influenced, and to make sure they are taught the value of, and equipped with ways to actively seek diverse and accurate information.
 And that is not just in response to the issue of misinformation and propaganda, but really it is simply a requirement for nurturing open minds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are however some considerations that need to be asked to ensure technology and the Internet can contribute positively, rather than negatively, to society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Firstly, we need to re-think online advertisement, which besides being a toxic market that is corrosive to the right to privacy, it is also a key enabler of the twisted dynamics that I just spoke about. It is online advertisement after all that is the primary cause of clickbaiting, with all the consequences that it brings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly we need to engage the tech giants and require an opening of their systems for algorithmic decision making. We just can not rely on systems that select, prioritize and carry information that operate in ways that are cloaked by trade secrets. Even if those algorithmic decisions might not be an immediate issue now, they very likely will be in the future and, as we know, rolling back technologies that have been in place for years is just too hard, and we instead should make sure we build them with all the ethical and social considerations in mind from the very beginning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;This text is adapted from my speech at re:publica 2017 in conversation with Garry Kasparov.&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
            <pubDate>Wed, 24 May 2017 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
            <link>https://nex.sx//blog/2017/05/24/manipulation-public-opinion.html</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://nex.sx//blog/2017/05/24/manipulation-public-opinion.html</guid>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>On the Banality of Attacks and on Mindful Engineering</title>
            <description>&lt;p&gt;Over the years of my experience assisting journalists and dissidents with matters of computer security, and researching the nature of the threats they face, I learned that those who don’t have access to security solutions and do not operate in a managed environment, are often not best served by the consumer technology they are normally provided with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a recognizable difference between the design of certain consumer technology and some other. Mobile phones, for example, are increasingly provided with operating systems that are designed — for the most part, at least — around the interests of end-users. Other technology, like personal computer’s operating systems, seem to be often designed around the interests of the Enterprise sector instead. It really depends on what appears to be the primary target market for the producer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To me, this is signified by the fact that among the many — and I mean, really a lot of — attacks that I have observed targeting members of civil society, the use of exploits is a rare sight. Mind, not just zero-day exploits, but even just exploits at all. The large majority of attacks that I observe leverage tricks as infection vectors that are very simply (ab)using features that are exposed by the operating system or mainstream consumer software, and that seem to be mostly intended for enterprise users. Rather than a lack of sophistication on the part of the state-sponsored actors orchestrating these attacks, I believe this rather indicates a dire state of overall security controls.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are definitely tactical advantages in using tricks rather than exploitation. For example, abusing features exposed by operating systems like Microsoft Windows or by primary consumer applications like Microsoft Office, or Adobe Reader, requires way less situational awareness. Attackers do not need to know which architecture, build, or version of the particular software targets use, and as such there is no need to spend resources and time crafting attacks that must be reliable. This is particularly true when the target of an attacker is a diverse demographic that does not operate within an uniformed technology stack as it generally is in corporate and government environments. Additionally, while attackers often look for that one weak entry point to exploit in the operations of corporations or government institutions, the targeting of activist and dissident groups is often opportunistic — except, of course, of some individuals who are of particular interest — and attackers seek instead to just compromise as many people as possible. As a matter of fact, it is common to see the same spearphishing email being sent in carbon copy to dozen of individuals, even working for different organizations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For these reasons, targeting activists, journalists, and dissidents using tricks is very likely way less expensive than using exploits, and might in fact result in a higher success rate. Consequently, this is driving up the numbers of attacks we witness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most common vectors for spearphishing attacks that I’ve observed in the last year involved the abuse either of Microsoft Office Macros and Packager Shell Objects, or the abuse of PowerShell or Windows Script Host. With perhaps the exception of Macros for Excel, all the remaining tricks are powered by features that are generally useless to regular users, and are rather thought for the Enterprise sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For some of them, I can’t even think of any reasonable legitimate use. For example: why should one be able to embed Windows executables inside a PowerPoint title slide and automatically launch them through a custom animation? &lt;em&gt;(Insert here a dozen more implicit question and exclamation marks.)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I understand. A lot has to do with enabling system administrators and software developers to automate some of their tasks. Yes, I am sure that PowerShell is great at that. I am also sure it is great for facilitating incident response in corporate environments. However, please don’t make those default options (or in the case of PowerShell, for example, no option at all). Organizations can provision the configuration they prefer, end users instead have to stick with what they’re given. I am all for rich features and plenty of possibilities, but I am also for security by default, not by choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me now demystify some of the most common responses I get when similarly ranting about these particular issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;“There is Antivirus software, they detect all that”&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Firstly, no. Secondly, any security design that relies on the efficacy of third party products that your user must discover and acquire is a ridiculous one.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;“Users should learn not to click on unsolicited links and attachments”&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Links and attachments are supposed to be clicked. It’s the whole point. If you expect users to be able to discriminate naturally between a legitimate email and a malicious one, you are detached from the reality of real world attacks. Attackers commonly befriend victims, impersonate their relatives and co-workers, and create all the pre-conditions to make the attack as credible as possible.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;“Users are warned when they are about to execute something dangerous”&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;div style=&quot;float: left;padding-right: 20px;padding-bottom: 5px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/blog/20170111/warning.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;That’s not always the case, but it is for some applications. However, it is also clear that vague, undescriptive warnings — like the one displayed on the side — are not enough. For example, in the case of some targeted attacks against dissidents in Iran my co-conspirator Collin and I have documented last year, the malware was delivered through malicious PowerPoint presentations that embedded multiple copies of the same executable in the title slide and launched it in the same way I described earlier. Why multiple copies? Because while at the first, or second, or third security warning dialog from Microsoft Office the victim might not allow the payload to execute, they most likely will at the fourth or fifth. We formalized this technique as Security Bypass by Annoyance.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;“Even if you disable one feature or another, there’s so many ways to compromise someone”&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;True. It still doesn’t mean however that we should leave all doors open. Reducing the number of possible attack points allows us to deal and watch for the fewer remaining ones more efficiently.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To this effect, my dear friend emdel and I at Security Without Borders have started aggregating tips &amp;amp; tricks to disable some of these most problematic features in a little experimental utility that is being assembled here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, I invite software producers — especially those who provide highly popular consumer applications — to stay informed on how some of their choices are being regularly abused, to stop blaming users, and to start practicing more mindful engineering.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
            <pubDate>Wed, 11 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
            <link>https://nex.sx//blog/2017/01/11/on-banality-of-attacks.html</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://nex.sx//blog/2017/01/11/on-banality-of-attacks.html</guid>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Interview with Hisham Almiraat — a story of Activism, Surveillance, and Freedom</title>
            <description>&lt;p&gt;It is a cloudy and rather cold day of October in a city that shall remain unnamed. I am meeting with Hisham Almiraat, a professional doctor and well respected democracy, human rights, and digital rights activist from Morocco. He is currently in self-exile fighting some unjust charges that could land him up to five years of prison. Hisham is an old acquaintance of mine, and while the occasions to meet in person have always been rare, our paths crossed in circumstances that were rather unfortunate several years ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hisham is part of the first generation of what he calls “digital dissidents” from his country, young people who found through blogs and the Internet a mean for intellectual liberation and political manifestation, in ways that were otherwise unavailable to them before. In the light of the Arab Spring, Hisham co-founds a citizen media outlet called Mamfakinch, which soon becomes one of the central resources for the people of Morocco to report and learn about what is happening in the streets of their cities, while the state media blacks out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/blog/20161209/hisham1.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;em&gt;Hisham Almiraat. Photo by Claudio Guarnieri.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the Summer of 2012 Mamfakinch is targeted with a computer attack with the intent of violating the computers of its members and infecting them with a powerful spy software called “Remote Control System” produced by the Italian company Hacking Team. That is when I learn of Hisham and his colleagues, and through my work with Citizen Lab, University of Toronto, end up first meeting him. The discovery of the attack against Mamfakinch was significant, as one among the very first documented cases of computer attacks using European-made technology for the persecution of political activists and journalists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We sit down in a crowded and loud pub, mostly lightened by candles, and we talk for few hours, about the Internet, technology, and their roles in modern society and in one’s political life. I know all the ins and outs of the computer attack he and his colleagues suffered, but I want to learn more about what led to it and what happened afterwards. What brought him to the political engagement that is very much asking for his own freedom now, and how — especially recently — has technology played such a central role in the events that unfolded and that ultimately brought us both here, sitting at this table, in a night of Autumn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hisham can speak at length about the history of Morocco, and analyzes with deep insight all the mechanics of an entire region that was caught by surprise as the Arab Spring unleashed across the entirety of North Africa. In what many called the Facebook Revolution, the Internet certainly played a crucial part in amplifying the cry for democracy as well as, as Hisham tells me, to inscribe from the very beginning the guiding principles of a massive protest movement that was to be non-violent. Technology did play a role in mobilizing and organizing people, and possibly expedited the spread of the movement through other countries, but it was also simply a tool in the hands of younger generations who years before started getting politicized. Soon enough, technology itself was turned against them as a mean to suppress the outburst of dissent of those years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ask Hisham what is the turning moment for him, and he tells me the story of how it all started.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It’s 2009. As you told me, Le Monde and its partner get in trouble in Morocco as a result of publishing an opinion poll, which revealed the 91% of the population was happy with the conduct of the current king. The protest campaign “I am the 9%” is born. How is this moment significant for you and generally for Morocco, in the light of the Arab Spring soon to come?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was the first instance I can recall when a community of progressive-minded bloggers took action and, pretty spontaneously, turned the nascent power of social media to their advantage. If I was to give a metaphor, it’s like sitting in the dark, knowing there are other people in the room — you can hear them breath, you can hear them move and talk but you can’t quite identify them. All of a sudden someone strikes a match and for a little while, while that flame is still going you get to see everybody’s faces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was that kind of a revealing moment. And it was a coming of age of a generation of bloggers who, frustrated as they were, by the systematic subjugation of the press, took it upon themselves to challenge, criticize and scrutinize power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So there it was, the first fait d’armes of a small but significant group of early digital dissidents that will play a major role in mobilizing and coordinating the efforts of a much larger movement, the so-called February 20 Movement, that will emerge in the fateful year of 2011.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You guys realize it is necessary for a critical citizen media outlet to exist, and Mamfakinch comes to exist. Do you remember when and how you and your colleagues come to that realization?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was outrage that created the first spark — outrage against the Moroccan government and its propaganda machine. A week before pro-democracy street protests were planned, the official state news agency, MAP, published a communiqué claiming that people they identified as protest leaders were calling off the demonstration. It was a blatant lie. We thought, if a publicly-funded news agency supposed to inform citizens, is spreading lies, maybe we could do something about it. Maybe it was time we launch our own “people’s news agency”. And that’s how the idea for a website came up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How big and what was the real objective of Mamfakinch, as the Arab Spring then starts getting prominent in Morocco as well?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We were frankly inspired by what other activists were doing in other countries in the region. Our aim was to circumvent the Moroccan media blackout over protests so that our countrymen and women know what was happening. We also wanted to offer a platform for dissident voices that were totally sidelined by state-owned media. Our ambition was also to do investigative work. And we did break stories related to corruption and nepotism within the regime. And while we never claimed to be objective (we were clearly on the side of the pro-reform, pro-democracy movement) we tried to abide by a set of self-imposed ethical rules.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At it’s early stage, the project was run by a dozen individuals. The early success of Mamfakinch (over a million unique visitors during the first weeks after launch) led to an influx of contributors. At some point we were about 30 individuals running the project as a collective with no hierarchy to speak of, and a very fluid publishing process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People would approach us to join the collective. If a candidate is endorsed by two members or more she gets in. People who want to publish were free to do so but had to respect an editorial charter that, among other things, valued non-violence and democratic values.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/blog/20161209/hisham2.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;em&gt;Hisham and I speaking. Photo by Daniel Moßbrucker, edited by Claudio Guarnieri.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;“Almiraat” isn’t your real name. Was it a conscious choice for you to use a pseudonym? Did anonymity play any role in Mamfakinch’s operations? Was there a sense of risk involved in your work?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It wasn’t a conscious choice at the beginning. Almiraat (“The Mirror” in Arabic) was the name I chose for my first blog that I started in 2007. It then became my pseudonym because everybody started calling me Almiraat. But then I realized how convenient it was not to use your real name, especially when you write critically about the Moroccan government. You can get into real trouble if they ever find out who you are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When, a couple of years later, I and a couple of friends co-founded Mamfakinch, it became clear that we may very well end up in the cross-hairs of the government at some point down the road. In fact, most contributors to the site volunteered time and effort on the condition that their identity was to be protected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;In 2012, Mamfakinch is attacked with Hacking Team software. Before that incident, did you and your team perceive surveillance as a threat? Did you have indications of Moroccan investment in surveillance technology as a mean for repression?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before the incident, there was a sense that the identity of the contributors to the website, much of whom put their careers in line to provide valuable input to us, needed to be protected. But we never realized what kind of capacity our adversary might have. And quite frankly, we never thought much of the government’s ability against us. We underestimated it. We were probably conscious of the fact that there were security vulnerabilities with regards to how to make a website that is collectively run, secure. Password management for example was always a problem. But we always trusted each member of the group to do their bid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turned out we were up against a highly sophisticated kind of a threat. We knew, as early as 2011, that Morocco was up to something when it was revealed that it spent €2 million in taxpayers money to purchase a mass surveillance system from French company Amesys. But even then we were not particularly alarmed — and maybe we should have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why do you think Mamfakinch was attacked and why in that particular moment?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We were attacked a couple of days after the website was awarded the Google-Global Voices Breaking Borders award. The award was a recognition of our efforts to use the Internet as a way of promoting public debate and democratic values. But it was probably also the moment when we became too visible for the regime’s taste. There were also other factors likely at play: the fact that the attention of international media was turning away from Morocco, focusing more of the unfolding tragedy in Syria and Yemen. Another likely motive is the fact that during that summer of 2012, Mamfakinch broke a series of stories pertaining to police brutality against protesters and exposed a high profile corruption and nepotism case against a minister in the government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other words, Mamfakinch was becoming a serious thorn on the side of the regime that they needed to do away with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Do you remember the day you were attacked? Can you describe what happened? Where were you?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I remember it was early in the morning. I opened my email as I would everyday. And there was this one email that stood out. It claimed to be from a whistleblower — someone who claimed (judging from the subject line) to send us a scoop they wanted it published. I guess I was lucky that morning because I was late for work so I never really opened it myself. Later in the day I learned that all the co-editors received the very same email. Most of them opened it. The file was empty. We didn’t make much of it that day. It was only a few days later that our tech guy raised the issue again. We learned that during that same week other activists in the region, especially in Bahrain, were hacked via infected emails. Our tech guy suggested almost jokingly that maybe we should look into that empty file. We did. It so happens that we knew just the right people who could help. We knew the Citizen Lab in Toronto did similar research work for activists in other parts of the world so we thought they were the right people to approach. And indeed, after a couple days, the diagnostic came back. It was a virus — and not any kind of virus for that matter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How did you feel both individually and collectively as you realize that Mamfakinch was indeed in the crosshair of the government?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first feeling is one of angst. You fear for the people who trusted you with their personal information and whose careers, and maybe even lives, you might have now put in harm’s way. But then this feeling is quickly overcome with anger because you know that this unique project that you’ve invested so much on and that you built on trust, has received a deadly blow. There was little chance that we could come out of this unscathed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What do you think was the real objective of the attack? Was it to identify your sources? Was it instigate fear in the members of Mamfakinch as they realized they were being watched? And what do you think was the most significant damage?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The initial objective of the government was, I think, to surreptitiously identify the people behind the project. Once identified it would be easy to intimidate them or attack them and discredit them. They were unlucky because we were able to seek help and identify the attack. But then again, the harm was done. Whether the regime was able to identify our members or not was no longer relevant. What lingered in everybody’s mind was that they were capable of doing it. And that possibility in and of itself is a victory for the government because the fear of being surveilled torpedoed the trust in the project, and effectively put an end to it. That’s how harmful this kind of technology is: it poisons the well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What happened after the attack? Did Mamfakinch survive?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once we discovered the attack we became acutely aware of the urgency of implementing digital security measures. But again, the harm was done. It didn’t matter whether our machines were clean or not, or whether we used encryption or not. They proved they could do it once. It means they can do it again. That put off a lot of people who volunteered contribution to the website. After a couple of months we went down from a team of about 30 regular contributors and co-editors into.. 3 people struggling to keep the website alive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a while it was clear the project could not survive. There was just not enough people willing to come forward. We had to close.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;With your experience, how effective do you think that digital surveillance can be to curb citizen journalism and protest movements?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the mid-2000, when blogging and social media peaked as a means of citizen journalism and activism, governments were still playing catch-up. They first tried to apply to the Internet what they were used to do offline: in other words, mainly trying to block websites and content they didn’t like. But that didn’t work as people always found a way to circumvent censorship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But then, especially after the Arab spring, autocratic governments realizing the disruptive power of the Internet decided they needed to control it. That’s when we’ve seen a kind of public-private partnership emerging as mainly western-based companies, realizing they can make loads of money selling spying technology to repressive regimes, came to the rescue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Surveillance was the perfect answer for those regimes: short of actually spying on the activities of every single one of their citizens they can instill the fear of being watched in the heart of every Internet user. If you know you can be watched you tend to self-censor and suppress your own expression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s how you turn the Internet, thought-of initially as an inherently democratic tool, into an Orwellian mass surveillance nightmare.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Couple of years later, you and some colleagues start a digital rights organization in Morocco called Association des Droits Numeriques (ADN). Was being subject to digital surveillance what led you into working more in that area of human rights?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fact of being a target has certainly played a role. Most importantly also, was the realization that without a political front, the battle for the Internet was going to be lost. It is important to protect personal information using technical fixes like encryption. But it’s also important to challenge power and to speak to power, to inform users, to challenge privacy violations in court and build a platform for civil society to express its concerns when it comes to Internet-related legislation and governance issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;At some point, the Moroccan government cracks down on ADN, and you are charged with destabilization of state security. What happened? Why are you being prosecuted?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think we are being given the Oscar for our whole careers as activists. By that I mean that what happened to us is only part of a larger post-Arab Spring crackdown on civil society actors in Morocco and across the region, targeting especially people who were intimately involved with the pro-democracy movement back in 2011. The Moroccan government were probably waiting for the opportunity to silence our work and they found it convenient to charge us now that the world attention is focused elsewhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What happened is that, in partnership with the UK-based Privacy International we published a report, in 2015, documenting multiple cases of unlawful electronic surveillance conducted against Moroccan academics, journalists and human rights activists. Three days after the report was published, the government opened a criminal investigation against me and ADN’s vice-president on charges of “Libelous accusations against a government body” and of “reporting a false crime”. Those charges carry up to 5 years in jail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another criminal investigation was later launched against me and some of my closest collaborators on a project called StoryMaker — a mobile app developed by a Dutch NGO, Free Press Unlimited, to help journalists and activists publish newsworthy stories. I was coordinating the training on the app and facilitating digital security training for vulnerable journalists and activists whom we taught how to use tactics like encryption.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because of my involvement in that project I was later charged with “Undermining State security”, a charge punishable by an additional 5 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Do you think there is a brighter future for Morocco and the region? And will the people this time be ready?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think when the next Spring comes, and I’m sure it will come, people will be ready, learn from our experiences, prepare for the worst and hope for the best.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hisham remains optimistic. His difficult condition hasn’t affected his spirit at all, and he rather seems more determined and inspired than ever. It is late night now, we hug, wish good luck to each other, and part ways. Hopefully next time we meet we shall instead celebrate his hopes becoming reality.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
            <pubDate>Fri, 09 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
            <link>https://nex.sx//blog/2016/12/09/interview-hisham-almiraat.html</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://nex.sx//blog/2016/12/09/interview-hisham-almiraat.html</guid>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>To Hack or Not To Hack</title>
            <description>&lt;p&gt;Nobody wants backdoors for the state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rather, nobody reasonable wants backdoors for the state. Backdoors are undisclosed accesses to circumvent protections — they create distrust in the affected technology and are an obvious security hazard. But what about hacking? This question is the subject of much discussion at the moment. Do we want the state to make use of computer hacking?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wait… why would we?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In democracies citizens are supposed to hold the power to determine the limits, role, rights, and responsibilities of the state. This power is an illusion. The reality is that we normally don’t fully understand what the state’s investigative powers are, and we don’t have hard evidence of their success or whether they are justified. It takes leaks or Freedom of Information Act requests to even form a blurred picture of what surveillance and intrusion technologies are adopted, and how frequently they are being used.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And while from a theoretical and technical point of view we might be in some position to contemplate what level of access the state should be granted, I am reluctant to endorse anything particular. Do we, as a security and hacking community, really have the responsibility and the burden to come up and provide feasible options for the state to penetrate and subvert the same technology we’re striving to protect and improve?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the arm wrestle that is power structures trying to acquire additional powers, I believe we should be the opposing force, and that rather than embracing and — let alone — proposing any given option, we should be contrarian voices, with the hope that the result — if any result is to be achieved — would be satisfying.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, why would we want to grant the state more power? Normally, that is what citizens should be challenging, rather than enabling. I know, there is always a tension between what would be ideal, and what is realistic. In an ideal world, states would not need to spy and snoop, but we don’t live in such a world. Still, history and recent leaks have shown authorities routinely abuse their power and, by all odds, granting them more power will likely lead to even more abuse. Acting on our ideals, even if they can’t be fully actualized, is an effective way to loudly voice such concern and to make sure that the least possible privileges are being granted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Truthfully, I have no expectation of preventing hacking from becoming a legitimized tool in the arsenal of a state — it largely is already, and if not, it is inevitable. However, I do believe we should do everything to ensure it is costly, and to oppose it when discovered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we find malware used by a state, we should expose it. If we find an exploit used by a state, we should expose it. Whichever the state is, whoever the victims are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is through this process of accountability that we can maintain a balance, and this process should be safeguarded and accepted as an unavoidable operational and economic cost of adopting invasive practices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am not going to be advocating and legitimizing the use of hacking by any state, to then wait for its exposure to be criminalized. I am not going to agree to government hacking. I might tolerate it, but still continue fighting it.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
            <pubDate>Sun, 16 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
            <link>https://nex.sx//blog/2016/10/16/to-hack-or-not-to-hack.html</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://nex.sx//blog/2016/10/16/to-hack-or-not-to-hack.html</guid>
        </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>
