<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        <title>Nex</title>
        <description>The personal website of Claudio Guarnieri, alias Nex.
</description>
        <link>https://nex.sx</link>
        <atom:link href="https://nex.sx/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
        
        <item>
            <title>Manipulation of Public Opinion</title>
            <description>&lt;p&gt;Manipulation of public opinion clearly isn’t anything new. It has traditionally been achieved by repeating over and over a specific message in the public and to the media to install a particular narrative that serves one’s interests. This commonly manifests with catchphrases which, just like commercial advertisement, are repeated endlessly until they become permanently ingrained in the public consciousness. We’ve seen it for example with the “blood on his hands” rhetoric being used against Snowden and Manning in the last years. We’re seeing it recently in the UK with “coalition of chaos” being used by the conservatives to refer to the opposition. And we’ve seen countless examples of that also by Trump during the 2016 campaign.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;The public is fundamentally a consumer of political advertisement.&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Social media has become an extension of this. Today’s Internet economic incentives foster an environment of clickbait and instant gratification, originally leveraged for online advertisement and moneymaking, but that it turns out is perfect too for catchphrase politics, particularly in a moment of resurgence of demonizing politics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With social media increasingly becoming a primary platform for the consumption of information, it also clearly has become a field where propaganda and misinformation campaigns play out. But the Internet doesn’t exist in a vacuum, it’s quite simply a reflection of society, with all good and bad that comes with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With much talk of fake news (which quite frankly, is a term that I believe should be abandoned, because it is imprecise and unhelpful for a constructive debate) and of social media bots, I think we’re seeing a concerning trend towards a techno-fatalism, that finds in technology a scapegoat for significant societal issues (as we’ve seen time and time again with the introduction in society of a new technology), and that as a result invokes some kind of techno-solutionism, which is just as problematic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are seeing some movements towards the over-regulation of content online. For example in Germany, where a law was passed that enforces fines of tens of millions of euros to companies who fail to enforce some appropriate and timely filtering of content and countering of “fake news”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are complex phenomena that require deep and dedicated study to fully understand. There is no solid indication yet of what is the measured impact (for example on elections) of false news and Twitter bots, and while they might very well have some, it is imperative that before implementing further laws and controls we have a good and documented view of what is the nature of this problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These issues need to be analyzed in the geographical and socio-political context in which they manifest. The impact of such phenomena will differ between countries that implement repressive policies with serious dangers involved in political manifestation, and say countries with a strong respect for the rule of law and human rights. These differences might warrant different reactions and countermeasures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;Firstly, it is reassuring to know that humans still lead the political debate.&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the matter of misinformation campaigns, Facebook recently stated for example that: “while we acknowledge the ongoing challenge of monitoring and guarding against information operations, the reach of known operations during the US election of 2016 was statistically very small compared to overall engagement on political issues.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A study by Stanford University comes to similar conclusions, and professor and co-author Matthew Gentzkow commented that “a reader of our study could very reasonably say, based on our set of facts, that it is unlikely that fake news swayed the election” and that “social media was an important but not dominant source of news in the run-up to the election”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In regards to the French elections, Oxford University published a paper that assessed the distribution of news over social media in the run-up to the first round and found that “the largest proportion of content being shared by Twitter users interested in French politics comes from professional news organizations. Information from political parties, government agencies and other experts is also being used. Still, 19.6 percent of the content being shared involves other kinds of political news and information. Yet the largest proportion of that content is not junk news but citizen-generated content”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And not only that, but that in regards to Twitter bots “by candidate, it appears that most of the candidates have roughly the same number of highly automated accounts generating traffic about them.”
 And yet this automated traffic amounted to roughly 7% of the total, according to the researchers at Oxford.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All this is to say that we need to step back a little and look at it with perspective in order to find appropriate and proportionate solutions that promote and respect the right to freedom of expression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A response driven by anxiety and panic is unlikely to be a constructive one and we don’t want to end up in a place where companies, instead of courts and the public opinion, are entitled to decide what is rightful content and what isn’t, and by extension we do not want to create regimes of over-censorship, because it is not by filtering that we solve bigotry and racism. Additionally, we might not realize that, while implementing certain restrictions or controls over some technology that might seem threatening to us, we might cause an unintended impact on the lives of others in other parts of the world. For example, a crack down on the right to anonymity online and enforcing service providers to police that, will necessarily mean for example that some human rights defenders in another country will not be able to do their work safely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That said, it is important that the public is well informed and it is not deceived. When we’ll get to the point where social media will be in fact the primary source of news, and by my reading it doesn’t seem to be there quite yet, the real answer to these issues will be education and media literacy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;quote&quot;&gt;Technology can’t be “trusted”, technology needs to be understood.&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And we need to make sure that especially generations to come will be prepared to enter in their political life with the right understanding of how technology works, of how media and social media work and how they can be influenced, and to make sure they are taught the value of, and equipped with ways to actively seek diverse and accurate information.
 And that is not just in response to the issue of misinformation and propaganda, but really it is simply a requirement for nurturing open minds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are however some considerations that need to be asked to ensure technology and the Internet can contribute positively, rather than negatively, to society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Firstly, we need to re-think online advertisement, which besides being a toxic market that is corrosive to the right to privacy, it is also a key enabler of the twisted dynamics that I just spoke about. It is online advertisement after all that is the primary cause of clickbaiting, with all the consequences that it brings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly we need to engage the tech giants and require an opening of their systems for algorithmic decision making. We just can not rely on systems that select, prioritize and carry information that operate in ways that are cloaked by trade secrets. Even if those algorithmic decisions might not be an immediate issue now, they very likely will be in the future and, as we know, rolling back technologies that have been in place for years is just too hard, and we instead should make sure we build them with all the ethical and social considerations in mind from the very beginning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;footnote&quot;&gt;This text is adapted from my speech at re:publica 2017 in conversation with Garry Kasparov.&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
            <pubDate>Wed, 24 May 2017 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
            <link>https://nex.sx//blog/2017/05/24/manipulation-public-opinion.html</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://nex.sx//blog/2017/05/24/manipulation-public-opinion.html</guid>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>On the Banality of Attacks and on Mindful Engineering</title>
            <description>&lt;p&gt;Over the years of my experience assisting journalists and dissidents with matters of computer security, and researching the nature of the threats they face, I learned that those who don’t have access to security solutions and do not operate in a managed environment, are often not best served by the consumer technology they are normally provided with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a recognizable difference between the design of certain consumer technology and some other. Mobile phones, for example, are increasingly provided with operating systems that are designed — for the most part, at least — around the interests of end-users. Other technology, like personal computer’s operating systems, seem to be often designed around the interests of the Enterprise sector instead. It really depends on what appears to be the primary target market for the producer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To me, this is signified by the fact that among the many — and I mean, really a lot of — attacks that I have observed targeting members of civil society, the use of exploits is a rare sight. Mind, not just zero-day exploits, but even just exploits at all. The large majority of attacks that I observe leverage tricks as infection vectors that are very simply (ab)using features that are exposed by the operating system or mainstream consumer software, and that seem to be mostly intended for enterprise users. Rather than a lack of sophistication on the part of the state-sponsored actors orchestrating these attacks, I believe this rather indicates a dire state of overall security controls.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are definitely tactical advantages in using tricks rather than exploitation. For example, abusing features exposed by operating systems like Microsoft Windows or by primary consumer applications like Microsoft Office, or Adobe Reader, requires way less situational awareness. Attackers do not need to know which architecture, build, or version of the particular software targets use, and as such there is no need to spend resources and time crafting attacks that must be reliable. This is particularly true when the target of an attacker is a diverse demographic that does not operate within an uniformed technology stack as it generally is in corporate and government environments. Additionally, while attackers often look for that one weak entry point to exploit in the operations of corporations or government institutions, the targeting of activist and dissident groups is often opportunistic — except, of course, of some individuals who are of particular interest — and attackers seek instead to just compromise as many people as possible. As a matter of fact, it is common to see the same spearphishing email being sent in carbon copy to dozen of individuals, even working for different organizations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For these reasons, targeting activists, journalists, and dissidents using tricks is very likely way less expensive than using exploits, and might in fact result in a higher success rate. Consequently, this is driving up the numbers of attacks we witness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most common vectors for spearphishing attacks that I’ve observed in the last year involved the abuse either of Microsoft Office Macros and Packager Shell Objects, or the abuse of PowerShell or Windows Script Host. With perhaps the exception of Macros for Excel, all the remaining tricks are powered by features that are generally useless to regular users, and are rather thought for the Enterprise sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For some of them, I can’t even think of any reasonable legitimate use. For example: why should one be able to embed Windows executables inside a PowerPoint title slide and automatically launch them through a custom animation? &lt;em&gt;(Insert here a dozen more implicit question and exclamation marks.)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I understand. A lot has to do with enabling system administrators and software developers to automate some of their tasks. Yes, I am sure that PowerShell is great at that. I am also sure it is great for facilitating incident response in corporate environments. However, please don’t make those default options (or in the case of PowerShell, for example, no option at all). Organizations can provision the configuration they prefer, end users instead have to stick with what they’re given. I am all for rich features and plenty of possibilities, but I am also for security by default, not by choice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me now demystify some of the most common responses I get when similarly ranting about these particular issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;“There is Antivirus software, they detect all that”&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Firstly, no. Secondly, any security design that relies on the efficacy of third party products that your user must discover and acquire is a ridiculous one.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;“Users should learn not to click on unsolicited links and attachments”&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;Links and attachments are supposed to be clicked. It’s the whole point. If you expect users to be able to discriminate naturally between a legitimate email and a malicious one, you are detached from the reality of real world attacks. Attackers commonly befriend victims, impersonate their relatives and co-workers, and create all the pre-conditions to make the attack as credible as possible.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;“Users are warned when they are about to execute something dangerous”&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;div style=&quot;float: left;padding-right: 20px;padding-bottom: 5px;&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/blog/20170111/warning.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;That’s not always the case, but it is for some applications. However, it is also clear that vague, undescriptive warnings — like the one displayed on the side — are not enough. For example, in the case of some targeted attacks against dissidents in Iran my co-conspirator Collin and I have documented last year, the malware was delivered through malicious PowerPoint presentations that embedded multiple copies of the same executable in the title slide and launched it in the same way I described earlier. Why multiple copies? Because while at the first, or second, or third security warning dialog from Microsoft Office the victim might not allow the payload to execute, they most likely will at the fourth or fifth. We formalized this technique as Security Bypass by Annoyance.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;“Even if you disable one feature or another, there’s so many ways to compromise someone”&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

    &lt;p&gt;True. It still doesn’t mean however that we should leave all doors open. Reducing the number of possible attack points allows us to deal and watch for the fewer remaining ones more efficiently.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To this effect, my dear friend emdel and I at Security Without Borders have started aggregating tips &amp;amp; tricks to disable some of these most problematic features in a little experimental utility that is being assembled here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, I invite software producers — especially those who provide highly popular consumer applications — to stay informed on how some of their choices are being regularly abused, to stop blaming users, and to start practicing more mindful engineering.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
            <pubDate>Wed, 11 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
            <link>https://nex.sx//blog/2017/01/11/on-banality-of-attacks.html</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://nex.sx//blog/2017/01/11/on-banality-of-attacks.html</guid>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Interview with Hisham Almiraat — a story of Activism, Surveillance, and Freedom</title>
            <description>&lt;p&gt;It is a cloudy and rather cold day of October in a city that shall remain unnamed. I am meeting with Hisham Almiraat, a professional doctor and well respected democracy, human rights, and digital rights activist from Morocco. He is currently in self-exile fighting some unjust charges that could land him up to five years of prison. Hisham is an old acquaintance of mine, and while the occasions to meet in person have always been rare, our paths crossed in circumstances that were rather unfortunate several years ago.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hisham is part of the first generation of what he calls “digital dissidents” from his country, young people who found through blogs and the Internet a mean for intellectual liberation and political manifestation, in ways that were otherwise unavailable to them before. In the light of the Arab Spring, Hisham co-founds a citizen media outlet called Mamfakinch, which soon becomes one of the central resources for the people of Morocco to report and learn about what is happening in the streets of their cities, while the state media blacks out.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/blog/20161209/hisham1.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;em&gt;Hisham Almiraat. Photo by Claudio Guarnieri.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the Summer of 2012 Mamfakinch is targeted with a computer attack with the intent of violating the computers of its members and infecting them with a powerful spy software called “Remote Control System” produced by the Italian company Hacking Team. That is when I learn of Hisham and his colleagues, and through my work with Citizen Lab, University of Toronto, end up first meeting him. The discovery of the attack against Mamfakinch was significant, as one among the very first documented cases of computer attacks using European-made technology for the persecution of political activists and journalists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We sit down in a crowded and loud pub, mostly lightened by candles, and we talk for few hours, about the Internet, technology, and their roles in modern society and in one’s political life. I know all the ins and outs of the computer attack he and his colleagues suffered, but I want to learn more about what led to it and what happened afterwards. What brought him to the political engagement that is very much asking for his own freedom now, and how — especially recently — has technology played such a central role in the events that unfolded and that ultimately brought us both here, sitting at this table, in a night of Autumn.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hisham can speak at length about the history of Morocco, and analyzes with deep insight all the mechanics of an entire region that was caught by surprise as the Arab Spring unleashed across the entirety of North Africa. In what many called the Facebook Revolution, the Internet certainly played a crucial part in amplifying the cry for democracy as well as, as Hisham tells me, to inscribe from the very beginning the guiding principles of a massive protest movement that was to be non-violent. Technology did play a role in mobilizing and organizing people, and possibly expedited the spread of the movement through other countries, but it was also simply a tool in the hands of younger generations who years before started getting politicized. Soon enough, technology itself was turned against them as a mean to suppress the outburst of dissent of those years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I ask Hisham what is the turning moment for him, and he tells me the story of how it all started.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It’s 2009. As you told me, Le Monde and its partner get in trouble in Morocco as a result of publishing an opinion poll, which revealed the 91% of the population was happy with the conduct of the current king. The protest campaign “I am the 9%” is born. How is this moment significant for you and generally for Morocco, in the light of the Arab Spring soon to come?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was the first instance I can recall when a community of progressive-minded bloggers took action and, pretty spontaneously, turned the nascent power of social media to their advantage. If I was to give a metaphor, it’s like sitting in the dark, knowing there are other people in the room — you can hear them breath, you can hear them move and talk but you can’t quite identify them. All of a sudden someone strikes a match and for a little while, while that flame is still going you get to see everybody’s faces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was that kind of a revealing moment. And it was a coming of age of a generation of bloggers who, frustrated as they were, by the systematic subjugation of the press, took it upon themselves to challenge, criticize and scrutinize power.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So there it was, the first fait d’armes of a small but significant group of early digital dissidents that will play a major role in mobilizing and coordinating the efforts of a much larger movement, the so-called February 20 Movement, that will emerge in the fateful year of 2011.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;You guys realize it is necessary for a critical citizen media outlet to exist, and Mamfakinch comes to exist. Do you remember when and how you and your colleagues come to that realization?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was outrage that created the first spark — outrage against the Moroccan government and its propaganda machine. A week before pro-democracy street protests were planned, the official state news agency, MAP, published a communiqué claiming that people they identified as protest leaders were calling off the demonstration. It was a blatant lie. We thought, if a publicly-funded news agency supposed to inform citizens, is spreading lies, maybe we could do something about it. Maybe it was time we launch our own “people’s news agency”. And that’s how the idea for a website came up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How big and what was the real objective of Mamfakinch, as the Arab Spring then starts getting prominent in Morocco as well?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We were frankly inspired by what other activists were doing in other countries in the region. Our aim was to circumvent the Moroccan media blackout over protests so that our countrymen and women know what was happening. We also wanted to offer a platform for dissident voices that were totally sidelined by state-owned media. Our ambition was also to do investigative work. And we did break stories related to corruption and nepotism within the regime. And while we never claimed to be objective (we were clearly on the side of the pro-reform, pro-democracy movement) we tried to abide by a set of self-imposed ethical rules.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At it’s early stage, the project was run by a dozen individuals. The early success of Mamfakinch (over a million unique visitors during the first weeks after launch) led to an influx of contributors. At some point we were about 30 individuals running the project as a collective with no hierarchy to speak of, and a very fluid publishing process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People would approach us to join the collective. If a candidate is endorsed by two members or more she gets in. People who want to publish were free to do so but had to respect an editorial charter that, among other things, valued non-violence and democratic values.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/blog/20161209/hisham2.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;em&gt;Hisham and I speaking. Photo by Daniel Moßbrucker, edited by Claudio Guarnieri.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;“Almiraat” isn’t your real name. Was it a conscious choice for you to use a pseudonym? Did anonymity play any role in Mamfakinch’s operations? Was there a sense of risk involved in your work?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It wasn’t a conscious choice at the beginning. Almiraat (“The Mirror” in Arabic) was the name I chose for my first blog that I started in 2007. It then became my pseudonym because everybody started calling me Almiraat. But then I realized how convenient it was not to use your real name, especially when you write critically about the Moroccan government. You can get into real trouble if they ever find out who you are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When, a couple of years later, I and a couple of friends co-founded Mamfakinch, it became clear that we may very well end up in the cross-hairs of the government at some point down the road. In fact, most contributors to the site volunteered time and effort on the condition that their identity was to be protected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;In 2012, Mamfakinch is attacked with Hacking Team software. Before that incident, did you and your team perceive surveillance as a threat? Did you have indications of Moroccan investment in surveillance technology as a mean for repression?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before the incident, there was a sense that the identity of the contributors to the website, much of whom put their careers in line to provide valuable input to us, needed to be protected. But we never realized what kind of capacity our adversary might have. And quite frankly, we never thought much of the government’s ability against us. We underestimated it. We were probably conscious of the fact that there were security vulnerabilities with regards to how to make a website that is collectively run, secure. Password management for example was always a problem. But we always trusted each member of the group to do their bid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turned out we were up against a highly sophisticated kind of a threat. We knew, as early as 2011, that Morocco was up to something when it was revealed that it spent €2 million in taxpayers money to purchase a mass surveillance system from French company Amesys. But even then we were not particularly alarmed — and maybe we should have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why do you think Mamfakinch was attacked and why in that particular moment?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We were attacked a couple of days after the website was awarded the Google-Global Voices Breaking Borders award. The award was a recognition of our efforts to use the Internet as a way of promoting public debate and democratic values. But it was probably also the moment when we became too visible for the regime’s taste. There were also other factors likely at play: the fact that the attention of international media was turning away from Morocco, focusing more of the unfolding tragedy in Syria and Yemen. Another likely motive is the fact that during that summer of 2012, Mamfakinch broke a series of stories pertaining to police brutality against protesters and exposed a high profile corruption and nepotism case against a minister in the government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other words, Mamfakinch was becoming a serious thorn on the side of the regime that they needed to do away with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Do you remember the day you were attacked? Can you describe what happened? Where were you?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I remember it was early in the morning. I opened my email as I would everyday. And there was this one email that stood out. It claimed to be from a whistleblower — someone who claimed (judging from the subject line) to send us a scoop they wanted it published. I guess I was lucky that morning because I was late for work so I never really opened it myself. Later in the day I learned that all the co-editors received the very same email. Most of them opened it. The file was empty. We didn’t make much of it that day. It was only a few days later that our tech guy raised the issue again. We learned that during that same week other activists in the region, especially in Bahrain, were hacked via infected emails. Our tech guy suggested almost jokingly that maybe we should look into that empty file. We did. It so happens that we knew just the right people who could help. We knew the Citizen Lab in Toronto did similar research work for activists in other parts of the world so we thought they were the right people to approach. And indeed, after a couple days, the diagnostic came back. It was a virus — and not any kind of virus for that matter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How did you feel both individually and collectively as you realize that Mamfakinch was indeed in the crosshair of the government?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first feeling is one of angst. You fear for the people who trusted you with their personal information and whose careers, and maybe even lives, you might have now put in harm’s way. But then this feeling is quickly overcome with anger because you know that this unique project that you’ve invested so much on and that you built on trust, has received a deadly blow. There was little chance that we could come out of this unscathed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What do you think was the real objective of the attack? Was it to identify your sources? Was it instigate fear in the members of Mamfakinch as they realized they were being watched? And what do you think was the most significant damage?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The initial objective of the government was, I think, to surreptitiously identify the people behind the project. Once identified it would be easy to intimidate them or attack them and discredit them. They were unlucky because we were able to seek help and identify the attack. But then again, the harm was done. Whether the regime was able to identify our members or not was no longer relevant. What lingered in everybody’s mind was that they were capable of doing it. And that possibility in and of itself is a victory for the government because the fear of being surveilled torpedoed the trust in the project, and effectively put an end to it. That’s how harmful this kind of technology is: it poisons the well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What happened after the attack? Did Mamfakinch survive?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once we discovered the attack we became acutely aware of the urgency of implementing digital security measures. But again, the harm was done. It didn’t matter whether our machines were clean or not, or whether we used encryption or not. They proved they could do it once. It means they can do it again. That put off a lot of people who volunteered contribution to the website. After a couple of months we went down from a team of about 30 regular contributors and co-editors into.. 3 people struggling to keep the website alive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a while it was clear the project could not survive. There was just not enough people willing to come forward. We had to close.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;With your experience, how effective do you think that digital surveillance can be to curb citizen journalism and protest movements?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the mid-2000, when blogging and social media peaked as a means of citizen journalism and activism, governments were still playing catch-up. They first tried to apply to the Internet what they were used to do offline: in other words, mainly trying to block websites and content they didn’t like. But that didn’t work as people always found a way to circumvent censorship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But then, especially after the Arab spring, autocratic governments realizing the disruptive power of the Internet decided they needed to control it. That’s when we’ve seen a kind of public-private partnership emerging as mainly western-based companies, realizing they can make loads of money selling spying technology to repressive regimes, came to the rescue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Surveillance was the perfect answer for those regimes: short of actually spying on the activities of every single one of their citizens they can instill the fear of being watched in the heart of every Internet user. If you know you can be watched you tend to self-censor and suppress your own expression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s how you turn the Internet, thought-of initially as an inherently democratic tool, into an Orwellian mass surveillance nightmare.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Couple of years later, you and some colleagues start a digital rights organization in Morocco called Association des Droits Numeriques (ADN). Was being subject to digital surveillance what led you into working more in that area of human rights?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fact of being a target has certainly played a role. Most importantly also, was the realization that without a political front, the battle for the Internet was going to be lost. It is important to protect personal information using technical fixes like encryption. But it’s also important to challenge power and to speak to power, to inform users, to challenge privacy violations in court and build a platform for civil society to express its concerns when it comes to Internet-related legislation and governance issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;At some point, the Moroccan government cracks down on ADN, and you are charged with destabilization of state security. What happened? Why are you being prosecuted?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think we are being given the Oscar for our whole careers as activists. By that I mean that what happened to us is only part of a larger post-Arab Spring crackdown on civil society actors in Morocco and across the region, targeting especially people who were intimately involved with the pro-democracy movement back in 2011. The Moroccan government were probably waiting for the opportunity to silence our work and they found it convenient to charge us now that the world attention is focused elsewhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What happened is that, in partnership with the UK-based Privacy International we published a report, in 2015, documenting multiple cases of unlawful electronic surveillance conducted against Moroccan academics, journalists and human rights activists. Three days after the report was published, the government opened a criminal investigation against me and ADN’s vice-president on charges of “Libelous accusations against a government body” and of “reporting a false crime”. Those charges carry up to 5 years in jail.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another criminal investigation was later launched against me and some of my closest collaborators on a project called StoryMaker — a mobile app developed by a Dutch NGO, Free Press Unlimited, to help journalists and activists publish newsworthy stories. I was coordinating the training on the app and facilitating digital security training for vulnerable journalists and activists whom we taught how to use tactics like encryption.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because of my involvement in that project I was later charged with “Undermining State security”, a charge punishable by an additional 5 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Do you think there is a brighter future for Morocco and the region? And will the people this time be ready?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think when the next Spring comes, and I’m sure it will come, people will be ready, learn from our experiences, prepare for the worst and hope for the best.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hisham remains optimistic. His difficult condition hasn’t affected his spirit at all, and he rather seems more determined and inspired than ever. It is late night now, we hug, wish good luck to each other, and part ways. Hopefully next time we meet we shall instead celebrate his hopes becoming reality.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
            <pubDate>Fri, 09 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
            <link>https://nex.sx//blog/2016/12/09/interview-hisham-almiraat.html</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://nex.sx//blog/2016/12/09/interview-hisham-almiraat.html</guid>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>To Hack or Not To Hack</title>
            <description>&lt;p&gt;Nobody wants backdoors for the state.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Rather, nobody reasonable wants backdoors for the state. Backdoors are undisclosed accesses to circumvent protections — they create distrust in the affected technology and are an obvious security hazard. But what about hacking? This question is the subject of much discussion at the moment. Do we want the state to make use of computer hacking?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wait… why would we?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In democracies citizens are supposed to hold the power to determine the limits, role, rights, and responsibilities of the state. This power is an illusion. The reality is that we normally don’t fully understand what the state’s investigative powers are, and we don’t have hard evidence of their success or whether they are justified. It takes leaks or Freedom of Information Act requests to even form a blurred picture of what surveillance and intrusion technologies are adopted, and how frequently they are being used.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And while from a theoretical and technical point of view we might be in some position to contemplate what level of access the state should be granted, I am reluctant to endorse anything particular. Do we, as a security and hacking community, really have the responsibility and the burden to come up and provide feasible options for the state to penetrate and subvert the same technology we’re striving to protect and improve?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the arm wrestle that is power structures trying to acquire additional powers, I believe we should be the opposing force, and that rather than embracing and — let alone — proposing any given option, we should be contrarian voices, with the hope that the result — if any result is to be achieved — would be satisfying.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, why would we want to grant the state more power? Normally, that is what citizens should be challenging, rather than enabling. I know, there is always a tension between what would be ideal, and what is realistic. In an ideal world, states would not need to spy and snoop, but we don’t live in such a world. Still, history and recent leaks have shown authorities routinely abuse their power and, by all odds, granting them more power will likely lead to even more abuse. Acting on our ideals, even if they can’t be fully actualized, is an effective way to loudly voice such concern and to make sure that the least possible privileges are being granted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Truthfully, I have no expectation of preventing hacking from becoming a legitimized tool in the arsenal of a state — it largely is already, and if not, it is inevitable. However, I do believe we should do everything to ensure it is costly, and to oppose it when discovered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we find malware used by a state, we should expose it. If we find an exploit used by a state, we should expose it. Whichever the state is, whoever the victims are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is through this process of accountability that we can maintain a balance, and this process should be safeguarded and accepted as an unavoidable operational and economic cost of adopting invasive practices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am not going to be advocating and legitimizing the use of hacking by any state, to then wait for its exposure to be criminalized. I am not going to agree to government hacking. I might tolerate it, but still continue fighting it.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
            <pubDate>Sun, 16 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
            <link>https://nex.sx//blog/2016/10/16/to-hack-or-not-to-hack.html</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://nex.sx//blog/2016/10/16/to-hack-or-not-to-hack.html</guid>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Letter on the Investigatory Powers Bill</title>
            <description>&lt;p&gt;The British government is in the process of reviewing and acting upon a draft to extend the surveillance powers of British police and intelligence forces. Many have criticized the pervasiveness of the proposed regulations, and currently a Review Committee of the British Parliament is open to receive feedbacks from the public. Following is the letter I submitted to the Committee to the Science and Technology Committee on the Investigatory Powers Bill. I invite all of you to &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.parliament.uk/business/committees/committees-a-z/commons-select/science-and-technology-committee/inquiries/parliament-2015/investigatory-powers-bill-technology-issues-inquiry-launch-15-16/commons-written-submission-form/&quot;&gt;express your opinions&lt;/a&gt; on a bill that might become an example for many other European countries to follow. You have time until the end of today, November 27th 2015.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Among the many chapters of the Investigatory Powers Bill, the ones concerning Equipment Interference and especially Bulk Equipment Interference are among the most concerning. In this letter I will focus on analyzing and commenting on such parts, however that is not to be considered as a silent approval of the remaining chapters of the charter, which I’m confident others will scrutinize in great depth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;equipment-interference&quot;&gt;Equipment Interference&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Equipment Interference, despite how loosely defined it is in the draft, remains a very intrusive and powerful instrument in the hands of law enforcement and intelligence agencies. In order to perform an Equipment Interference, the authorized agency would engage either into installing physical hardware  implants inside a selected computer or mobile device, or, more likely, utilize software vulnerabilities or malicious network attacks in order to remotely gain access to the selected device and install a monitoring software (commonly known as “malware” or “spyware”) to covertly collect information, including documents, emails, chat messages, and voice calls, stored and produced by the user through his or her daily use of the device. By compromising the end-user devices, such as a mobile phone or computer, it grants not only access to communication on transit, as regular passive wiretapping, but to any information that the target has produced, sent, or received in the past, presently, and in the future. It is, in fact, the most intrusive method of monitoring one can employ, and therefore it must be used with care. The definitive ability for law enforcement and intelligence agencies to employ these methods is not something to be granted lightly, and the strictest regulation and strongest oversight have to be adopted, if at all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a moment where the use of computer compromise is still a very nebulous practice and it is little understood by policy makers, it is imperative that in legitimizing it now, we not only take into consideration the very immediate threats to society and the immediate investigative requirements, but that we deeply analyze the potential impact, the unexpected collateral damage, and the inevitable long term effects. The adoption of offensive technologies such as the use of equipment interference tends to foster a market of surrounding services, prompting existing and new commercial ventures to invest into the production and sale of intrusive systems, such as highly sophisticated monitoring software as well as software vulnerabilities and exploits. Software vulnerabilities are logical flaws or flaws in design, commonly present in computer software, that can be leveraged (through the use of specifically crafted payloads, commonly known as “exploits”) to locally or remotely execute some malicious code that enables an attacker to maintain access and persistence over the compromised device. While it isn’t necessarily always the case, vulnerabilities and exploits are a very common vehicle to perform a compromise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While understanding the flaws of existing computer systems is an important practice that needs to be protected, disregarding the importance of improving defenses and capitalizing on the secrecy of security vulnerabilities can have a severe damaging effect over the overall security of our systems. Since legitimate targets make use of the very same technology of any other regular Internet and computer user, if a security hole is left unpatched, it remains open for others to discover and abuse, including criminal organizations and foreign state-actors. It is therefore important to remember that technology is an universal good, and if it is maintained insecure for the benefit of certain intelligence or investigative powers, it will remain insecure for everybody else as well, including the same police and intelligence forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because of this, I believe it is important to limit as much as possible the widespread adoption of such offensive technologies, and commit to the best possible extent to develop defenses and assist software vendors in remediating to the flaws their products are affected by. While the need to adopt end-point compromise is understandable and the tactical advantage of secretly maintain the exclusivity on software vulnerabilities might seem desirable, I would recommend to prevent the abuse of such vulnerabilities and possibly establish a process to responsibly disclose them to the respective vendors for the benefit not only of British citizens, but global society as a whole. This would involve the British Government reporting security vulnerabilities they find to companies like Apple, Google, or Microsoft so that everyones systems can be patched, and secured against attack. A security flaw can’t be delimited to a selected part of the population, despite how despicable and dangerous it might be, but it does in fact affect everybody, with no exclusion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In particular, certain passages of the Equipment Interference chapter seem to be particularly concerning. First of all, the charter suggests that the use of Equipment Interference would be limited to the investigation of serious crimes, matters of national security, and economic interests of the United Kingdom as long as those interests also relate to national security. I believe that it would be beneficial to provide a better and more narrow definition of what such crimes and matters would involve. The draft doesn’t for example define what could be classified as a “serious crime” and leaves largely up to speculation how economic interests of the UK could directly relate to immediate threats to its national security.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the process of defining what types of crimes and of targets Equipment Interference might be used against, I invite the committee to carefully evaluate whether such definitions could be prone to unexpected interpretations. For example, the clause in Article 83(g) specifies that Equipment Interference could be used against “equipment that is being, or may be used, to test, maintain or develop capabilities relating to interference with equipment for the purpose of obtaining communications, private information or equipment data”. Such definition appears too loose, it doesn’t specify an intent or a particular criminal behavior, and it might be construed to investigate legitimate security research, which would dangerously discourage British researchers and security experts to do their much needed work. I recommend, for example, such point to be taken out of the bill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since the safety of modern operating systems and network communications heavily relies on the integrity and ethical behavior of software vendors and service providers, I find Article 101 to be concerning. Such Article would effectively coerce Internet Service Providers, hosting providers, software vendors, and others, into sabotaging the integrity of automatic updates, web pages, and many other types of served content, into serving malicious code to invisibly compromise the end-point of the customer or user. This could very likely cause a chilling effect that would damage the trust the users invest into their service providers, and consequently also damage legitimate businesses. Additionally hijacking the legitimate functioning of such services might also lead to unexpected collateral damage and compromising additional users that might not be the intended targets of the investigation, effectively disrespecting their rights and invading their private lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;bulk-equipment-interference&quot;&gt;Bulk Equipment Interference&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chapter 3, Bulk Equipment Interference Warrants, besides inheriting all the fundamental problems I illustrated above, would extend the power of intelligence services into using Equipment Interference to a degree to I find deeply concerning. A Bulk Equipment Interference warrant would effectively grant intelligence services the license to compromise computer systems at large, without limitations of scope, numbers, location, or type of activity such systems is used to perpetrate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Extraordinarily, Clause 135 specifies that “bulk equipment interference is not targeted against particular person(s), organization(s) or location(s) or against equipment that is being used for particular activities”. Since in technical terms, actively compromising a computer systems requires at the very least to identify the nature of such system, the introduction of Bulk Equipment Interference appears as an attempt of intelligence services at obtaining the ability to opportunistically compromise any system they might deem interesting. It is unclear to what end such a power is sought. No operational case has been made, and I cannot conceive of one that would justify such extreme powers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My best guess is that the goal of the power is indeed to deploy Equipment Interference in an untargeted manner, compromising a large number of computers is to establish a strategic and tactical vantage point in case the access to such systems might prove fruitful in future and yet unidentified circumstances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This could not only lead to the compromise of large numbers of personal systems of innocent and unsuspicious Internet users, but also to the compromise of legitimate businesses and foreign institutions. For example, Article 136(3) specifies that a computer system is relevant for compromise under a Bulk Equipment Interference warrant “if any communications and private information are held on or by means of the system”. Under such terms, intelligence services could be legitimized in the attack and compromise of foreign Internet Service Providers and software vendors, as we have in fact observed through past disclosures on international press with the disclosure of GCHQ’s attacks of the Belgian Belgacom telecommunications provider, known for providing connectivity to European institutions, and the SIM cards manufacturer Gemalto. In both cases, the British GCHQ was found involved into breaking into unsuspecting European legitimate technology and Internet businesses in order to obtain a tactical advantage, identify and monitor the activity of their customer base, and potentially use the obtained access as a trampoline for further attacks. Besides being legally, ethically, and morally questionable, these intrusions have necessarily caused operational and financial damage to those businesses, who are not a threat to nationality security, which is plainly unacceptable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe that the introduction of Bulk Equipment Interference warrants would undermine the trustworthiness of global Internet services as well as foster an unaccountable use of disproportionate force. Given the inherit dangers and risks involved into directly breaking into computer systems, and the immense powers and access to information it can provide, providing intelligence services a way to operate at large and unchecked, would greatly destabilize the already precarious state of security of Internet-connected devices worldwide. I believe that Bulk Equipment Interference warrants should be removed from the Investigatory Powers Bill, and eventually, the use of untargeted compromise of computer systems be explicitly forbidden.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
            <pubDate>Fri, 27 Nov 2015 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
            <link>https://nex.sx//blog/2015/11/27/letter-investigatory-powers-bill.html</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://nex.sx//blog/2015/11/27/letter-investigatory-powers-bill.html</guid>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>On Export Controls</title>
            <description>&lt;p&gt;You can ignore it, minimize it or dismiss it, but there is a problem. The systematic abuse of surveillance systems against journalists, activists and political dissidents is a documented fact. There have been &lt;a href=&quot;https://resistsurveillance.org/reports.html&quot;&gt;numerous reports&lt;/a&gt; in the last years which show that the use of spyware to suppress dissent and cover corruption isn’t an isolated event. It’s a sad reality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Very often these attacks are carried out by oppressive governments around the world with the help of tools and services provided by Western companies, who have been repeatedly discovered and exposed, but are still operating with impunity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;regulation-or-not&quot;&gt;Regulation or not&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The policy making and privacy communities identified export controls as a potentially viable solution to increase the oversight and the accountability for those who market these invasive techonologies around the world. The scheme is very simple: companies willing to sell technologies classified within a selected group outside of a given region, will have to obtain a license from their local government; the licensing authority will evaluate the risks involved in such sale and decide whether to grant or reject the license; if companies are caught exporting to unlicensed countries, they can incur in legal penalties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tricky part is defining the technologies that need to be licensed accurately enough to not damage those ones that are not the original targets for such controls. Security researchers first and foremost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Privacy activists claim that the ongoing implementation of export controls - for example recently by the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.theguardian.com/technology/2014/nov/06/spyware-exports-licence-new-eu-rules-military-applications&quot;&gt;European Union&lt;/a&gt; - isn’t harming researchers in any way. A large faction of the security community claims the opposite. I don’t know where the truth stands. What I know is that there is no inclusiveness in this debate, which is starting to appear instead like a rough-and-tumble fight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I do have my doubts on export controls. I’m in no position to judge whether security researchers are harmed by them or not. This is something that should be subject to rigorous meaningful debate. I mostly question their effectiveness in their current shape.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’ll never hear export controls advocates say they are a perfect solution, but just a stepping stone. What I find bizarre is that while many legal experts from several European Union member states deem the use of intrusion software to be unconstitutional, we’re now debating on how can we properly and safely export it abroad. Where’s our integrity?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While speaking with legal experts on the matter and with licensing authorities themselves, it seems there is a common agreement that regulating technology itself is a bad idea. What they’re attempting to achieve instead is to discriminate the intentions of the license applicants and determine whether there are the legal and human rights conditions to allow companies to make business in the given country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m skeptical. I find it very arrogant to pretend to be able to effectively determine the legitimacy of intents not only of the applicant, but of the acquiring country as well. I doubt anybody can have the proper insight in the political, social and cultural conditions of foreign countries at any point in time and be able to make accurate judgements upfront. I can also imagine that political alliances and economic interests will largely take precedence over objective concerns of human rights abuses. Libya was an ally of many and an important economic partner, until suddenly everyone realized Gaddafi was a ruthless dictator.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, if the intent is to control surveillance profiteers who lack any moral compass or ethical principles, shouldn’t we expect them to simply move their businesses abroad probably under way less democratic oversight and accountability?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, assuming there is a concrete risk of collateral damage for security researchers as a result of this regulation, and considering the issues I explained above, are export controls a good idea in the first place?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t know. I do not think export controls are going to stop a booming surveillance industry or prevent the abuses that are occurring so commonly nowadays. I don’t think anything will.
However, if export controls can be a viable tool for punishing the ones repeatedly working in order to empower dictatorships, I’m not against them. I want liability, accountability and justice for those who refuse to recognize the harm they caused and who refuse to help mitigate it. Let me tell you, out of the many cases I’ve seen - where some victims even went to jail or into exile for their dissent - there hasn’t been a single instance where the suppliers of the regimes humbly acknowledged the incident, let alone assisted in remediation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Surveillance vendors are the root cause for this problem and I find troubling that they’re capitalizing on the legitimate concerns of the same security researchers they’ve harmed. They make no contributions to our community and should have no part in this debate, which they are instead polluting and manipulating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;researchers-do-need-protection&quot;&gt;Researchers do need protection&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most significant concerns expressed within the security community seem to relate specifically to the licensing of exploits and software vulnerabilities. Frankly, when reflecting on export controls I never even considered exploits. Firstly because I rarely find them used in the surveillance abuses I observe, and secondly because policy makers always reassured me they were not going to be regulated due to the technical difficulties surrounding them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a matter of fact, it is still not clear to me whether that’s the case. I had no part in drafting any export control legislation, nor am I well-informed on any particular implementation. If software vulnerabilities might in fact fall within the current controls, these would have to be the non-negotiable terms I’d require:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The regulation must in no way affect the free flow of security research done in the public interest, especially when provided to the public.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The regulation must in no way prevent security researchers from reporting vulnerabilities to bug bounties, directly to the vendors or through other intermediaries. The process of researching, discovering and disclosing software vulnerabilities is sacred to the improvements of our systems, and must therefore be preserved and protected. As &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/scarybeasts/status/536257476023578624&quot;&gt;Chris Evans put it&lt;/a&gt;, “&lt;em&gt;regulate those who massively profit from putting others at risk&lt;/em&gt;” instead.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The regulation must in no way affect the distribution of software, including commercial, that is intended for security testing, auditing and defense purposes. I’m hopeful there are ways to define semantic differences between security products and surveillance services.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The regulation should not apply to any free and open source software.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If it is not possible to guarantee these basic requirements, then I would agree that an implementation of an export control legislation must be avoided. Perhaps we can achieve accountability through other means. Collateral damage is bad, but impunity is just as bad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;time-to-evolve&quot;&gt;Time to evolve&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nobody is intentionally trying to obstruct security research. If there was no involvement of the security research community in the regulatory process, it’s probably because the policy makers mistakenly did not recognize the possibility of collateral damage. They probably thought they had it figured out and we were not there to prove them wrong. It’s our fault as much as theirs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a lesson to learn. Security has grown to be an asset in the hands of a very diversified pool of actors: researchers, hackers, governments, corporations, profiteers, scumbags, activists, politicians. As a security community we need to be more participant in the public and political debate, because nobody is going to protect our interests and preserve our rights for us. We have a role in society, and we have the duty to be active players in shaping its course.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Security and technology have become major political agenda items and they will be regulated, whether we like it or not. Avoiding a meaningful participation is an abdication of responsibility.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
            <pubDate>Sun, 15 Feb 2015 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
            <link>https://nex.sx//blog/2015/02/15/on-export-controls.html</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://nex.sx//blog/2015/02/15/on-export-controls.html</guid>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>All we know of NSA and Five Eyes malware</title>
            <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note: all the information contained in this essay are extracted from documents that have already been previously published by a number of news organizations at different times.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Snowden revelations have instigated a global outcry for privacy and empowered a more informed and critical analysis of the growing adoption of mass “passive” surveillance. However, the use of “active” surveillance and targeted attacks are commonly deemed as a necessary evil.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After years of publications, and even a massive commercial speculation, on the nature of state-sponsored attacks, particularly by China and Russia, it comes to no surprise that Western governments are also engaged in malware attacks. However, we still know very little on their capabilities and sophistication.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What we are learning is that it isn’t anymore just a matter of pure intelligence or counter-terrorism. A large portion of the attacks we’re seeing from all fronts are mostly political and sometimes economic. In few occasions they’re even in support of military missions. In a climate of fatigue from endless wars, modern day’s imperialism is carried through network packets and conflicts are played in the dark, across submarine cables and Internet routers, far from the sight of the public or the press.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to comprehend the true nature of the 21st century’s intelligence and military complex, it’s important to investigate and report on the infiltration capabilities of governments around the world, with no exceptions. If we are selective on the information the public is given, we will obtain a false picture of the ongoing war for Internet and information dominance and we won’t be able to build neutrally secure systems. There’s no space for nationalism in technology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-genie-project&quot;&gt;The GENIE Project&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All the active collection and offensive activities pursued by NSA are funded under a program &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.spiegel.de/media/media-35660.pdf&quot;&gt;a document published by &lt;em&gt;Der Spiegel&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; calls GENIE. In NSA’s own words “&lt;em&gt;the GENIE project plans, equips, and conducts Endpoint operations that actively compromise otherwise intactable targets and complement Midpoint programs that passively eavesdrop on communication links&lt;/em&gt;”. Among other things the budget includes “&lt;em&gt;sustaining covert domestic&lt;/em&gt;” surveillance:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: right;&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/blog/20150127/nsa_domestic.png&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;i&gt;Source: Der Spiegel&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And spending tens of million of dollars &lt;em&gt;covertly&lt;/em&gt; acquiring 0day vulnerabilities from third parties in a very samaritan program named “&lt;em&gt;Community Investment&lt;/em&gt;”:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: right;&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/blog/20150127/nsa_community.png&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;i&gt;Source: Der Spiegel&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much of what I’m going to illustrate in this essay is likely to be financed through the GENIE project, whose figures are staggering. NSA allocated more than 650 million dollars in 2013 alone, with the projected budget passing the billion dollars in 2017.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is unrealistic to expect to understand the depth and the reach of NSA’s malware programs given the amount of resources they are provided with. However thanks to technical research and the journalistic publications of the last year, we’re able to reconstruct some of the missing parts and we can try to put the puzzle back together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;malware-for-mass-surveillance&quot;&gt;Malware for mass surveillance&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Several documents released by &lt;em&gt;Der Spiegel&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;The Intercept&lt;/em&gt; in the last year demonstrate that the exploitation and infiltration of computers often complements the “passive” collection by providing entrance into systems and networks that would otherwise be invisible to the mass surveillance infrastructure. The separation between mass and targeted surveillance is becoming blurry as we learn of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.spiegel.de/international/world/ghcq-targets-engineers-with-fake-linkedin-pages-a-932821.html&quot;&gt;attacks against Internet Service Providers&lt;/a&gt;, of &lt;a href=&quot;https://firstlook.org/theintercept/2014/03/20/inside-nsa-secret-efforts-hunt-hack-system-administrators/&quot;&gt;targeting of system administrators&lt;/a&gt; and systematic &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.wired.com/2013/09/nsa-router-hacking/&quot;&gt;compromise of Internet routers&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dismissing the inherent problems of government hacking as a “necessary and proportionate” use of force is clearly a superficial and dangerous underestimation of the ongoing activities of governments around the world to sabotage the security and integrity of computer systems and of core Internet infrastructure. NSA is excelling at it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;float: right;text-align: right;margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/blog/20150127/implant_exfiltration_link.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/blog/20150127/implant_exfiltration_link.png&quot; width=&quot;400px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;i&gt;Source: Der Spiegel&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.spiegel.de/media/media-35672.pdf&quot;&gt;A document published by &lt;em&gt;Der Spiegel&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; shows that “&lt;em&gt;active implants&lt;/em&gt;”, a fancy term for malware, are used to “&lt;em&gt;copy traffic and direct a copy past a passive collector&lt;/em&gt;”. In other words, NSA is creating and deploying dedicated malware with the sole purpose of intercepting traffic they’d otherwise not be able to collect (or collect in clear) and route it through passive collectors that can then pipe it into NSA’s massive collection machinery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More specifically, they install malware on “&lt;em&gt;network infrastructure devices&lt;/em&gt;” to either collect “&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;an entire link without selection&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;” or alternatively do “&lt;em&gt;targeted copying&lt;/em&gt;”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m not sure how to emphasize this better. &lt;strong&gt;They’re compromising PBXs and similar core infrastructure with malware to mirror entire phone carrier links&lt;/strong&gt;. Let that sink in for a second.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;clear: both;&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;float: left;margin-right: 10px;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/blog/20150127/implant_hammermill_bravenickel.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/blog/20150127/implant_hammermill_bravenickel.png&quot; width=&quot;400px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;i&gt;Source: Der Spiegel&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just to put a name on it, we learn from the same document that an implant called &lt;strong&gt;BRAVENICKEL&lt;/strong&gt; is the one used to perform the bulk collection from the link layers. &lt;strong&gt;HAMMERMILL&lt;/strong&gt; is instead used for selective interception of traffic, which can then be either sent to the NSA’s passive collection systems or to TAO, possibly for more ad-hoc monitoring operations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As explained by a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.spiegel.de/media/media-35671.pdf&quot;&gt;different document&lt;/a&gt;, also published by &lt;em&gt;Der Spiegel&lt;/em&gt;, we learn that more specifically HAMMERMILL is provided with what appear to be two plugins. &lt;a href=&quot;/assets/blog/20150127/implant_hammerchant.png&quot;&gt;HAMMERSTEIN to collect VPN key exchanges, and HAMMERCHANT which instead is used to target VoIP traffic&lt;/a&gt;. The active collection of keys becomes critical in an attempt to systematically defeat encrypted communications, as better illustrated in &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.spiegel.de/international/germany/inside-the-nsa-s-war-on-internet-security-a-1010361.html&quot;&gt;this article&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;clear: both;&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;malware-of-all-flavors&quot;&gt;Malware of all flavors&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If there is one thing I can say for a fact, is that NSA has malware of all flavors. They have malware for all sorts of devices, platforms, architectures and networks. Their malware programs probably amount to dozens and NSA certainly has a different code name for each and every one of them. It is practically impossible to identify and understand all of them, but we can at least start with the ones that occur more often across the Snowden documents published so far. In the case of NSA, the principal malware programs seem to be &lt;strong&gt;VALIDATOR&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;UNITEDRAKE&lt;/strong&gt;, and &lt;strong&gt;STRAITBIZARRE&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;VALIDATOR&lt;/strong&gt; is an implant used to gain first access on the target device, collect some preliminary information and enable the subsequent deployment of a larger and more sophisticated malware framework. It is unclear what are its specific capabilities, but documents from the ANT catalog published by Der Spiegel in December 2013 suggest that it is at least available for Windows systems as well Internet routers. The SCHOOLMONTANA, &lt;a href=&quot;/assets/blog/20150127/implant_validator_sierramontana.png&quot;&gt;SIERRAMONTANA&lt;/a&gt;, and STUCCOMONTANA are BIOS backdoors that in fact enable persistence to VALIDATOR on different models of Juniper routers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;float: left;margin-right: 10px;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/blog/20150127/implant_somberknave.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/blog/20150127/implant_somberknave.png&quot; width=&quot;400px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;i&gt;Source: Der Spiegel&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SOMBERKNAVE is a Windows software implant that can enable VALIDATOR to exfiltrate data even from air-gapped machines by providing “&lt;em&gt;covert internet connectivity for isolated targets&lt;/em&gt;”. If there is a Wireless card available, SOMBERKNAVE will attempt to silently associate with any available WiFi and exfiltrate the stolen information through it. Lesson learned: an air-gapped machine isn’t air-gapped as long as it has hardware that can establish any kind of network connection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, as anticipated, VALIDATOR is just a reconnaissance tool, a dropper. The following stage of a typical attack would likely involve the deployment of a larger, full-featured and more sensitive implant, generally UNITEDRAKE or STRAITBIZARRE.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;UNITEDRAKE&lt;/strong&gt; is an extensible and modular framework which is provided with a large number of plugins that perform different collection functions, including GROK, a keylogger, SALVAGERABBIT, a USB exfiltration module, FOGGYBOTTOM, which presumably steals history and other information from Internet browsers, GUMFISH, which takes snapshots from a webcam, CAPTIVATEDAUDIENCE, to record audio from the embedded microphone, and &lt;a href=&quot;/assets/blog/20150127/wistfultoll.png&quot;&gt;WISTFULTOLL&lt;/a&gt;, to perform machine reconnaissance and available for STRAITBIZARRE as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;UNITEDRAKE has been reported in the past in connection with QUANTUM and FOXACID, and despite probably being one of the principal deployments from TAO, it seems to be simply a general purpose malware framework.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not much else is known about UNITEDRAKE.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;STRAITBIZARRE&lt;/strong&gt; appears to be the largest and most sophisticated malware programs in TAO’s arsenal. It’s a cross-platform implant available on Linux, Windows as well as mobile platforms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;float: right;text-align: right;margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/blog/20150127/implant_straitbizarre.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/blog/20150127/implant_straitbizarre.png&quot; width=&quot;400px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;i&gt;Source: Der Spiegel&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main goal of STRAITBIZARRE is to provide an interface for a large variety of software and hardware implants to exfiltrate data. The ANT catalog published by &lt;em&gt;Der Spiegel&lt;/em&gt; in 2013 contains few examples of such implants including &lt;a href=&quot;/assets/blog/20150127/cottonmouth_sbz.png&quot;&gt;COTTONMOUTH&lt;/a&gt;, a USB hardware implant which infiltrates in the target network, &lt;a href=&quot;/assets/blog/20150127/toteghostly_sbz.png&quot;&gt;TOTEGHOSTLY&lt;/a&gt;, a STRAITBIZARRE based implant for Windows Mobile phones, and &lt;a href=&quot;/assets/blog/20150127/dropoutjeep_sbz.png&quot;&gt;DROPOUTJEEP&lt;/a&gt;, a STRAITBIZARRE based implant for Apple iPhones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.spiegel.de/media/media-35674.pdf&quot;&gt;document&lt;/a&gt; from which the slide on the side is extracted goes in great length explaining how STRAITBIZARRE implants are used to exfiltrate data from systems that would otherwise be inaccessible or that would require phyisical access to the running device.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;float: left;margin-right: 10px;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/blog/20150127/quantumdns_shooter.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/blog/20150127/quantumdns_shooter.png&quot; width=&quot;400px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;i&gt;Source: Der Spiegel&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.spiegel.de/media/media-35664.pdf&quot;&gt;document&lt;/a&gt; recently published by Der Spiegel shows how computers infected with STRAITBIZARRE can be turned into disposable and non-attributable “Shooter” nodes part of the QUANTUM infrastructure. These nodes can then receive messages from TURBINE, NSA’s Command &amp;amp; Control system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, as shown in the diagram on the left, a QUANTUM Shooter (or TAO Shooter) is actively participant in QUANTUM attacks as it is instructed by NSA’s TURBINE to send specifically crafted responses to selected targets and hijack DNS, HTTP or any type of traffic NSA has a QUANTUM attack for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;clear: both;&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All in all, STRAIBIZARRE is probably what would keep me up at night.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;clear: both;&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As of now, there are no indications that either UNITEDRAKE or STRAITBIZARRE have been discovered in the wild, although it is probable that some of the prestigious malware attacks we’ve observed in the past and commonly attributed to the US - such as Stuxnet, Duqu and Flame - might be related to one of the two.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;float: left;margin-right: 10px;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/blog/20150127/implant_warriorpride.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/blog/20150127/implant_warriorpride.png&quot; width=&quot;400px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;i&gt;Source: Der Spiegel&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite having a probably unmatched budget and level of sophistication, NSA obviously isn’t the only member of the Five Eye in the malware business. Documents recently &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.spiegel.de/international/world/new-snowden-docs-indicate-scope-of-nsa-preparations-for-cyber-battle-a-1013409.html&quot;&gt;released by Der Spiegel&lt;/a&gt; demonstrate that Five Eyes are in fact collectively developing &lt;strong&gt;WARRIORPRIDE&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.spiegel.de/media/media-35665.pdf&quot;&gt;described by the Canadian CSEC&lt;/a&gt; as a “scalable, flexible, portable CNE platform” unified across Five Eyes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly to the malware programs illustrated so far, WARRIORPRIDE also appears to be a complex modular toolkit, provided with a variety of plugins, including some the CSEC explains to be particularly useful for reconnaissance and identification of foreign CNE implants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;clear: both;&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, WARRIORPRIDE is also a multi-platform framework. Records from a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.spiegel.de/media/media-35662.pdf&quot;&gt;GCHQ document&lt;/a&gt; released by &lt;em&gt;Der Spiegel&lt;/em&gt; show for example that an &lt;a href=&quot;/assets/blog/20150127/implant_warriorpride_iphone.png&quot;&gt;iPhone implementation has been created as well&lt;/a&gt;, and that it has been approved as a QUANTUM-enabled implant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Along with the recent trove of CNE documents, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.spiegel.de/media/media-35668.pdf&quot;&gt;Der Spiegel also published QWERTY&lt;/a&gt;, a keylogger module which appears to be part of the WARRIORPRIDE framework. While we know that the Canadians certainly make use of WARRIORPRIDE, strings in one of the QWERTY binaries suggest that the Australian Defense Signals Directorate (DSD), now just known as Australian Signals Directorate (ASD), might have had a part in the development:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/blog/20150127/qwerty_dsd.png&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, the XML definition file for the 20123.sys file from QWERTY shows that it depends on WzowskiLib and CNELib:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[code:xml]
	&lt;comments&gt;
		&lt;team&gt;None&lt;/team&gt;
		&lt;platforms&gt;Windows NT, Windows 2000, Windows XP (32/64 bit), Windows 2003 (32/64 bit)&lt;/platforms&gt;
		&lt;rightsRequired&gt;System or Administrator (if Administrator, I think the DriverInstallationUtility will generate some logs)&lt;/rightsRequired&gt;
		&lt;files&gt;None&lt;/files&gt;
		&lt;dllDepend&gt;None&lt;/dllDepend&gt;
		&lt;pluginsDepend&gt;U_HookManager v1.0, Kernel Covert Store v1.0&lt;/pluginsDepend&gt;
		&lt;librariesDepend&gt;CNELib v2.10, WzowskiLib v2.1&lt;/librariesDepend&gt;
		&lt;associatedImplantId&gt;20121&lt;/associatedImplantId&gt;
	&lt;/comments&gt;
[/code]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;float: left;margin-right: 10px;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/blog/20150127/warriorpride_wzowski.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/blog/20150127/warriorpride_wzowski.png&quot; width=&quot;400px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;i&gt;Source: Der Spiegel&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A different &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.spiegel.de/media/media-35688.pdf&quot;&gt;deck from Canadian CSEC&lt;/a&gt; contains a slightly modified version of the slide illustrated previously, this time mentioning Wzowski as a “5-eyes API” WARRIORPRIDE is implemented with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can deduce that WzowskiLib and CNELib both are libraries collectively developed and used by USA, UK, Canada, Australia and New Zealand as a foundation for developing private as well as shared malware kits, including but not exclusively WARRIORPRIDE.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;clear: both;&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is clear now that Five Eyes, especially other than the NSA I imagine, joined efforts to share resources and collectively develop a unified malware program.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;so-what-is-regin&quot;&gt;So what is Regin?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of November, &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/headhntr&quot;&gt;Morgan Marquis-Boire&lt;/a&gt; and I published together with &lt;em&gt;The Intercept&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://firstlook.org/theintercept/2014/11/24/secret-regin-malware-belgacom-nsa-gchq/&quot;&gt;a large collection of samples&lt;/a&gt; from a large and sophisticated malware framework commonly identified as &lt;strong&gt;Regin&lt;/strong&gt;, identified during a long investigation into the &lt;a href=&quot;https://firstlook.org/theintercept/2014/12/13/belgacom-hack-gchq-inside-story/&quot;&gt;Belgacom hack&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was immediately clear that Regin was sophisticated enough to be coming from a Western government, and finding it used against Belgacom was a clear indication that GCHQ might have been responsible. However, I have to admit, I originally didn’t think that any agency other than NSA could have been able to produce a kit as sophisticated as Regin. I soon realized I was wrong.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We know that Regin has been used in the Belgacom hack attributed to - or rather confessed by - the British GCHQ. First documented ties between Regin and GCHQ came with documents released by The Intercept having specific mentions of tools and modules, &lt;a href=&quot;https://theintercept.imgix.net/wp-uploads/sites/1/2014/12/legspin.png?auto=compress%2Cformat&amp;amp;q=90&quot;&gt;LEGSPIN&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://theintercept.imgix.net/wp-uploads/sites/1/2014/12/hopscotch.png?auto=compress%2Cformat&amp;amp;q=90&quot;&gt;HOPSCOTCH&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://securelist.com/blog/research/68438/an-analysis-of-regins-hopscotch-and-legspin/&quot;&gt;identified by Kaspersky as part of the Regin framework&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://theintercept.imgix.net/wp-uploads/sites/1/2014/12/legspin.png?auto=compress%2Cformat&amp;amp;q=90&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While working on &lt;em&gt;Der Spiegel&lt;/em&gt; publication, I started becoming increasingly convinced that Regin might in fact have been DAREDEVIL, what appears to be the GCHQ principal malware program, also mentioned in the screenshot above. All we knew was that Regin was used by GCHQ, so it might as well have been the case. However, my interpretation changed when I noticed this extract from the WARRIORPRIDE slide presented before:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/blog/20150127/warriorpride_daredevil.png&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This line can be open to interpretation, but it strongly suggests that WARRIORPRIDE and DAREDEVIL might in fact be different code names for the same malware program; what we commonly call Regin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, researchers from &lt;a href=&quot;http://securelist.com/blog/research/68525/comparing-the-regin-module-50251-and-the-qwerty-keylogger/&quot;&gt;Kaspersky were able to tie QWERTY to Regin&lt;/a&gt; by finding very clear similarities with a Regin keylogger module in their possession. Kaspersky also showed that QWERTY isn’t functional alone and it instead requires the 50225 Regin module, responsible for kernel-mode hooking. As a side note, I believe 50225 to be U_HookManager mentioned as a plugin dependency in the XML file presented above.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is significant because it provides a more concrete identification of Regin to a documented malware program from the Five Eyes. As we know that QWERTY is in fact a WARRIORPRIDE module, we might deduce that Regin is likely to be WARRIORPRIDE itself. An additional, but a bit stretched, interpretation might be that DAREDEVIL is a derivation of WARRIORPRIDE or that they might be so closely compatible, that Regin could in fact be the combination of the two.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;float: right;text-align: right;margin-left: 10px;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/blog/20150127/quantum_daredevil_sbz.png&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/blog/20150127/quantum_daredevil_sbz.png&quot; width=&quot;400px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;i&gt;Source: Der Spiegel&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For what it’s worth, there appears to be no evidence or mention of WARRIORPRIDE being used by NSA in any of the documents that have been published so far. What we know however, is that along with STRAITBIZARRE (yes, they mispelled it), DAREDEVIL/WARRIORPRIDE is enabled as a QUANTUM implant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This however isn’t surprising. In relation to the Belgacom hack, &lt;em&gt;Der Spiegel&lt;/em&gt; previously revealed that the infiltration, while operated by GCHQ, was in fact executed through a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.spiegel.de/international/world/ghcq-targets-engineers-with-fake-linkedin-pages-a-932821.html&quot;&gt;QUANTUM attack&lt;/a&gt;. We can deduce that members of Five Eyes, especially NSA and GCHQ, commonly share infiltration techniques and infrastructure and possibly coordinate to overcome one’s potential technical or legal limitations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;clear: both;&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;conclusions&quot;&gt;Conclusions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is very hard to have a clear understanding of the CNE and malware capabilities of NSA, GCHQ and Five Eyes as a whole. There is a large variety of programs and code names and it is clear that many of them are designed in such a way to be compatible and speak the same protocols. In some cases we can expect them to share parts of their code base as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The resources at their disposal are enormous, likely unmatched, and certainly their technical sophistication is equally remarkable. Assuming that Regin might in fact be WARRIORPRIDE, we can conclude that we still haven’t seen any of NSA’s malware programs in action. And if we did, we haven’t been able to identify which program they correspond to. My best bet is still on Flame.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Attribution is hard, and many criticize attempts of it as pretentious and most likely wrong. While I’m generally supportive of calling things for what they are, I’m learning that attribution of Western intelligence agencies attacks is incredibly hard. Regin is the closest we have got so far, and still, we likely won’t be able to differentiate one member of the Five Eyes from the others as a sole responsible for a given attack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point much of what is known, and partly even what I explained here, is largely speculative. It is imperative that the technical community keeps conducting analysis of the information at our disposal, connect the dots and fill the blank spots left. Share what you have, publish what you know. Don’t hold back.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
            <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jan 2015 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
            <link>https://nex.sx//blog/2015/01/27/everything-we-know-of-nsa-and-five-eyes-malware.html</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://nex.sx//blog/2015/01/27/everything-we-know-of-nsa-and-five-eyes-malware.html</guid>
        </item>
        
        <item>
            <title>Manipulation of Terror</title>
            <description>&lt;p&gt;I’m angry. I was angry when I woke up with the news of the inhuman attacks in France and I’m angrier now as I observe the reactions. Nationalists are spreading hate, fanatics are attacking Muslims, governments are capitalizing on this tragedy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div style=&quot;float: right;padding-left: 20px;padding-bottom: 5px;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://order-order.com/2015/01/12/richs-monday-morning-view-99/&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/blog/20150112/hypocrites.jpg&quot; height=&quot;600px&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While millions verse on the streets to defend freedom of the press, world leaders join the chorus. How convenient it is to stand united for our liberties now, while not long ago our same governments were &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dailymail.co.uk/news/article-2697194/Outrage-France-country-world-ban-pro-Palestine-demos.html&quot;&gt;banning peaceful demonstrations&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.nytimes.com/2013/08/22/us/manning-sentenced-for-leaking-government-secrets.html?pagewanted=all&amp;amp;_r=0&quot;&gt;jailing whistleblowers&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://freedom.press/blog/2014/08/documenting-arrests-journalists-ferguson&quot;&gt;arresting journalists&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.theguardian.com/uk-news/2014/jan/31/footage-released-guardian-editors-snowden-hard-drives-gchq&quot;&gt;threatening news organisations&lt;/a&gt;. Free speech was not attacked just these last few days, but it has been undermined in Western societies for a long time, often by the same leaders that are now waving &lt;em&gt;Je suis Charlie&lt;/em&gt; signs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To seal this climate of hypocrisy, even delegations from some of the most shameless oppressors of free press &lt;a href=&quot;https://storify.com/tometty/staunch-defenders-of-free-press-attend-solidarity&quot;&gt;joined the march&lt;/a&gt; in Paris yesterday. Egypt, Turkey, Saudi Arabia, United Arab Emirates and others were all there chanting “freedom of speech” along with the French population, while back home bloggers and journalists are tortured, jailed and their voices are being suppressed. Disgusting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And while the world mourns the victims of hate, the machinery of control will get in motion. We’ll hear calls for censorship, for tighter border control and we’ll see intelligence agencies mask their incompetence blaming their failures on a lack of resources. Surveillance reforms will halt, our debate on privacy will be deemed insensitive and we’ll be called irresponsible for publishing more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This shouldn’t be a moment to give in for more control and to lose the small victories we conquered in the last years. It shouldn’t be a moment to think of retaliation. It should be a moment to demand answers on how even the authoritarian solutions of surveillance and war we accepted after 9/11 failed us again. It should be a moment of realization that fear and hysteria didn’t help us, and that we should know better. The last decade of war on terror left an entire region devastated, our liberties corroded and gave birth to even more hate and a militarized Internet. Let’s not repeat the same mistakes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Censorship won’t stop the criminals. Ignorance won’t protect the innocents. Mass surveillance won’t save lives. War won’t bring democracy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Liberty, however, might bring some peace.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
            <pubDate>Mon, 12 Jan 2015 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
            <link>https://nex.sx//blog/2015/01/12/manipulation-of-terror.html</link>
            <guid isPermaLink="true">https://nex.sx//blog/2015/01/12/manipulation-of-terror.html</guid>
        </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>
